<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A remembrance for the living to pray for the dead made by a Father of the Soc. of Iesus.</title>
            <author>Mumford, J. (James), 1606-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26206</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09386719</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09386719</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42934</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51595)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42934)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1312:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A remembrance for the living to pray for the dead made by a Father of the Soc. of Iesus.</title>
                  <author>Mumford, J. (James), 1606-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>175, 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[St. Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Liturgy.</term>
               <term>Prayers for the dead.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42934:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REMEMBRANCE FOR THE LIVING TO Pray for the Dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made by a Father of the Soc. of Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>By the Prayers of the Holy Cath. Church, &amp; the wholeſome Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Altar, &amp; by Almes giuen for their Soules, it is not to be doubted, but the DEAD are holpen, that they may be dealt withall more mercifully, by our Lord, then their Sinnes haue deſerued. <bibl>
                  <hi>S. August. Serm.</hi> 32. <hi>de verb. Apoſt. tom.</hi> 10.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>symbol of Society of Jesus</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. Anno 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42934:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42934:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Deuout and Charitable READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ORD</hi> (ſayth holy Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, <hi>Pſal. 8.) What is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thou art mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of him?</hi> The Hebrew word <hi>Enoſch,</hi> which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in this place vſeth to ſignify <hi>Man,</hi> doth moſt properly ſignify a moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable forgetfull Creature: So that in the language of Scripture, a Man &amp; a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture most miſerable, and moſt forgetfull, is all one. This forgetfulnes is chiefly in things of the other life, which though they be neuer ſo important neuer ſo much inculcated; yet they find either no place at all, or the very leaſt &amp; last in our thoghts.</p>
            <p>I did not therefore without particular reaſon entitle this briefe Treatiſe, <hi>A Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance for the liuing to pray for the dead:</hi> for I thinke <hi>(deare Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi> that if thou haſt the hart of a Man, and not a ſtone in place of a hart, that this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42934:3"/>
               <hi>Remembrance</hi> will stir thee vp, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foard farre more aſsistance to theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streſsed Soules in Purgatory, then thou didst vſe to doe, meerly for want of due <hi>Remembrance, Reflection,</hi> and <hi>Conſideration</hi> of this matter.</p>
            <p>I haue in this Treatiſe made much vſe of a litle Book lately ſet forth in Latin of the ſame ſubiect; for I found in it diuers points briefly touched which ſeemed to me moſt worthy of longer Conſideration. I haue done my beſt to obſerue that method, and vſe that plaineſſe of ſtyle, which might moſt help my Reader to carry away my whole diſcourſe. Sweet <hi>IESV,</hi> who didst loue all Soules ſo dearly, that thou didst powre out the laſt droppe of thy ſacred bloud for them; graunt I beſeech thee, euen by this exceſſe of thy Charity, that we may not be ſo vncharitable to thoſe very Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, whom thou didst loue ſo tenderly, as to neglect their complaints, to ſlight their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and to leaue them without due aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in their miſeries.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42934:3"/>
            <head>A Remembrance for the Liuing, to pray for the Dead.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides many who er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneouſly think there is no ſuch matter is a <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that it is a vaine thing to pray for the dead; there be many who either for want of ſufficient inſtruction in that which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, or by inconſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of what they belieue, do paſſe ouer this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant buſines of praying for the dead ſo coldly, as that they think they do inough to help their owne ye a Chriſts owne, Brother, if they do but ſay, <hi>God rest his ſoule;</hi> which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42934:4"/>
is a moſt vnmercifull manner of proceeding For if we ſaw our litle Brother falne into the fier, we ſhould neuer be ſo hard-harted as to ſee him broile there, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelues it were charity inough to throw a little drop of water into the fier, ſomewhat to aſſwage his torments. And ſo, I know not how it comes to paſſe, that many flatter themſelues with the name of good-natur'd &amp; kind-harted Creatures, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding take ſo litle to hart this extreme neceſſity of their Brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that their thoughts are buſied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout nothing leſſe, then relieuing them. The intention therefore of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Treatiſe is firſt (though very briefly) to rectify the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of thoſe who thinke, and belieue amiſſe of <hi>Purgatory.</hi> Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly more at large to ſtirre vp in the will of all faithfull belieuers an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent deſire to redreſſe the vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable miſeries of theſe diſtreſſed Soules.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42934:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> PVRGATORY proued by all kind of ſacred Authority.</head>
               <p n="1">1. FIrſt, I muſt put my Reader in mind, that it commeth all to one, to proue that Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers do profit the Dead, &amp; to proue a <hi>Purgatory;</hi> for prayers can ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profit thoſe dead who are in Heauen, nor thoſe dead who are in Hell, and are paſt our help. Thoſe dead then who can receaue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by our Prayers, muſt neyther be in Heauen, nor in Hell, but in a third place which we call <hi>Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> where being detayned to ſuffer for their ſinnes not fully ſatisfied for, do ſtand in need of the help of their liuing brethren. To pray for theſe ſoules we hould it Piety, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety to deny them this reliefe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This we prooue, firſt by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the old Teſtament. In
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42934:5"/>
the ſecond Booke of the Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees <hi>Cap.</hi> 12. it is recorded, how the moſt pious and valiant <hi>Judas Machabaeus,</hi> hauing to this end made a gathering of twelue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand drachmes of ſiluer, did ſend this mony to <hi>Jeruſalem, That ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice might be offered for the ſins of the dead.</hi> And this Scripture addeth: <hi>A holy therfore, &amp; wholſome thought it is to pray for the dead, that they may be freed from their ſinnes.</hi> Hence it is cleare that the Iewes did hold prayer for the dead, &amp; conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly a <hi>Purgatory,</hi> ſeeing that they did all contribute for the making vp of this great ſumme of money to procure, <hi>that ſacrifice might be offered for the ſins of the dead.</hi> And this pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cuſtome of praying for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, is vntill this very day kept, and obſerued by the Iewes. Laſtly &amp; chiefly, this cuſtome is recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by Scripture, as <hi>holy,</hi> &amp; <hi>wholſome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wil perhaps ſay
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42934:5"/>
that theſe two Books of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees</hi> be not Canonical Scripture. I anſwere, that a thouſand and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt three hundred yeares ago, theſe books were defined to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, by the Councell of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage:</hi> in which S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelfe being preſent, did ſubſcribe to this definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Councell. The words of the Councel <hi>can</hi> 47. are: <hi>The Canonicall Scriptures be theſe: Geneſis, Exodus &amp;c. the 2. Books of the Machabees.</hi> And S. Auſtin ſaith <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>de Ciuit. c.</hi> 36. <hi>The Books of the Machabees not by the Iewes but by the Church are held for Canonicall.</hi> And S. Hierome <hi>in Prolog. Although the books of the Machabees be not in the Canon of the Iewes, yet by the Church they are reckoned among the historyes of diuine volumes.</hi> If therefore we wil receiue the Canon of Scripture from the Church, our queſtion is at an end; if we will not, we may make queſtions without end. So we ſee <hi>Luther</hi> himſelfe calleth into
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42934:6"/>
queſtion the authority of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyps,</hi> &amp; ſaith <hi>in Praefat noui Testam.</hi> that he eſteemeth this booke, <hi>ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther written with a Propheticall, nor Apostolicall ſpirit,</hi> &amp; yet our Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, who are ſo well skilled in the ſpirit, ſcarce eſteeme more any one booke of ſcripture. But by the way, I would aske of them how (if the Apocalyps be true Scripture) <hi>Luther</hi> can be a true Saint? For in the end of the Apocalyps <hi>cap.</hi> 22. it is ſaid: <hi>If any man shall diminish from the words of the booke of this Prophecy, God shall take away his part from the booke of life.</hi> But <hi>Luther</hi> tooke away all the words of this Prophecy, ſaying <hi>it was not written with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall ſpirit.</hi> Ergo, <hi>God shall take away his part from the booke of life.</hi> So dangerous a thing it is to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card Scripture.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Secondly I anſwer, that no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t can deny theſe books of the <hi>Machabees</hi> to be at leaſt of farre greater authority, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42934:6"/>
of any profane Author in the world, and that far more credit is to be giuen to the writer of them, then ought to be giuen to any man that euer did, or ſhal write hiſtory. For you your ſelues giue theſe Books a place in your Bibles: which honour you would deny to the faithfulleſt hiſtory-writers in the world: Neither can you deny, but that there may well be made a doubt whether theſe books be the word of God or no, ſeing we haue brought ſo great proofes, to proue that they are Gods Word. Well then ſay I, if credit be to be giuen to any hiſtory that euer was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, much more is it to be giuen to this. It is therfore true that <hi>Judas Machabaeus,</hi> who was then high Prieſt and the chiefe man amongſt Gods onely people, did cauſe this great ſumme of money to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and ſent to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> that <hi>Sacrifice might be offered for the ſins of the dead.</hi> It is true that the people,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42934:7"/>
and the onely people of God did contribute money very liberally to this end. It is alſo queſtionles true, that the Prieſts of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> hauing receaued this money, did offer Sacrifice for the ſins of the dead. And it is moſt true, that the ancient and moſt graue writer of this hiſtory doth commend it as a thing, <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>Wholſome to pray for the dead, that they may be freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſins.</hi> And all this by the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> by the whole Church of God in her pureſt age, as <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> and <hi>S. Hierome</hi> do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, was held ſo true, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued it to be Scripture. Shall we thinke, that both the Church of the Iewes (which then was the only true Church in the world) and of the primitiue Chriſtians (the pureſt Church that euer Chriſt had) did ſo generally maintaine an Errour fond, &amp; ſuperſtitious, as Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts call <hi>Prayer for the dead?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. As for the new Teſtament I ſhal
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42934:7"/>
haue a neceſſary occaſion in the next Chapter to cite many places: therefore now I will content my ſelfe with this one. <hi>S. Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> brings this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to prooue the Reſurrection: <hi>What will they do, who are baptized for the dead? if the dead do not riſe at all, to what end are they baptized for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? 1. Cor.</hi> 15. As if he would ſay, to what end do men do pennance for the dead? If there be no reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, why do they do pennance for them? This and no other can be the ſenſe of theſe words: For what other Baptiſme, but the Baptiſme of pennance (ſo <hi>S. Marke</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Luke</hi> do call it) can with profit be taken for the dead? And heere <hi>S. Paul</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his argument fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is profitably done for the dead; for els whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he preſſeth ſo hoatly thoſe words, <hi>To what end are they baptized for them?</hi> one mighty eaſily anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, <hi>to no end.</hi> This much for Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:42934:8"/>6. That the Apoſtles did ordaine Prayer to help the ſoules of the dead, is taught in playne words by <hi>S. Chryſostome: Jt was not rashly ordained by the Apostles, that in the dreadfull mysteryes, Commemoration should be made of the dead: for they knew that from thence, there commeth to the dead much gaine &amp; profit. Hom.</hi> 69. <hi>ad pop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. But if we would wiſh an euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proofe, that the Apoſtles did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Prayer for the dead, to the end they might be freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſins; what proofe could we haue greater, then to haue this written by ſome Diſciple of the Apoſtles themſelues? This you ſhall ſee how abundantly it is performed. The Scripture telleth vs, that among the true Belieuers who did cleaue vnto <hi>S. Paul, Denis</hi> the <hi>Areopagite</hi> was one, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. The ſame <hi>S. Denis</hi> ſpendeth the whole ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his booke <hi>de Eccleſiastica Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchia,</hi> in telling vs ſuch things,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42934:8"/>
                  <hi>Quae diuino instituto ſuper ſanctè qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcentibus fiunt,</hi> as by diuine ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are done ouer thoſe who haue repoſed holily. And amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g others, this is one, that, <hi>Venerabilis Praeſul precem ſuper eo ſacratiſsimam peragit: the venerable prelate doth ſay ouer the dead party, a moſt holy prayer.</hi> And afterwards he tels vs the contents of this moſt holy prayer. <hi>Precatur oratio illa diuinam Clementiam, vt cuncta dimittat per infirmitatem hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admiſſa peccata defuncto. That prayer doth beſeech the diuine Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that he would pardon vnto the dead man, his ſins committed through hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane frailty.</hi> Thus writeth this great diſciple of S. <hi>Paul.</hi> Is it pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to belieue him, or no? Did the prime diſciples of the Apoſtles vſe ſuperſtition?</p>
               <p n="8">8. I come now to the authority of the whole Church in her pureſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. The Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> of which I ſpake before, not onely approueth the Books of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42934:9"/>
for true Scripture, but by name imbraceth <hi>prayer for the dead.</hi> In the firſt councell of <hi>Nice. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 65. it was ordained, <hi>That when a Bishop died, notice should be giuen of his death to all Churches and Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steryes in the parish, that prayer might be made for him.</hi> But who can tell vs better the vniuerſall cuſtome of the Church, then the greateſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of the Church, who did ſee with his eyes that which he wrote with his pen; &amp; therfore although he were a man and might erre in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, yet of this which he did ſee ſhine before his eyes, he could not be ignorant; and it can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not but be imprudence not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue him, for els whom may we prudently belieue? <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> then writeth thus, <hi>l. de cura pro mort. c.</hi> 1. <hi>We read in the books of Machabees ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice offered for the dead, but although it were no where at all read in the old Testament, yet notwithstanding the authority of the vniuerſall Church is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42934:9"/>
not ſmall, which shineth with this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, where the remembrance of the dead hath place in the prayers of the Priest, which are powred out to our Lord God at the Aultar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere you ſee firſt the <hi>Machabees</hi> accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted part of the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Secondly, that although ſacrifice for the dead were not Scripture, yet being practiſed by the whole Church we haue ſufficient warrant to thinke it well done. Thirdly that the vniuerſall Church did ſhine with this cuſtome of offering ſacrifice for the dead. Let vs grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that <hi>S. Austin</hi> as a man might erre in the two firſt points; yet in this third, that the Church did ſhine in his dayes with this cuſtome of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing for the dead, he could not be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, no more then the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Doctor of <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge</hi> can be ignorant, that in <hi>England</hi> ſeruice is ſaid in the Engliſh to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue. Wherfore I ſay, it muſt needs be imprudence not to belieue him,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42934:10"/>
who ought in prudence as much to be belieued, as any man ought to be in a thing which he cannot but know. Now, if I belieue that the vniuerſall Church did ſhine with this cuſtome of offering ſacrifice for the dead (as in prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I muſt) how can I in prudence thinke that the vniuerſall Church, euen in that her golden age, was ſtained with ſuch a profane Errour, as Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants hold this to be? It is (ſaith the ſame <hi>S. Austin Ep.</hi> 118. <hi>ad Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar.</hi>) inſolent madnes to diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which is practiſed by the whole Church all the world o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. And why ſo? Becauſe, <hi>he that will not heare the Church, let him be vnto thee, as a Heathen or Publican. Matth.</hi> 18. Becauſe, <hi>the gates of hell cannot preuaile against her. Matth.</hi> 16. Becauſe, <hi>the is the pillar &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of truth. 1. Tim. 3.</hi> The Church then being the <hi>foundation of truth,</hi> may we not well cry out with S. <hi>Paul; O mad-men who hath be witched
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42934:10"/>
you not to obey the truth? Gal. 3.</hi> For was not <hi>Iohn Caluin,</hi> thinke you, bewitched when he ſpake theſe words: <hi>Before a thouſand, and three hundred yeares</hi> (ſaith <hi>Caluin</hi> aboue an hundred yeares ago) <hi>it was by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome receiued, that prayers should be made for the dead: but they all, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe were ingulfed in an errour. lib. 3. Iustit. c. 5:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Caluin,</hi> as boldly, as if it were cleere that for thirteene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares togeather none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all vnderſtood the Scripture ſo well as he. But by his leaue, I think I may be of the contrary opinion, &amp; I am very confident that <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> had as good a wit, ſtudied as much, was aſſiſted as much by the holy Ghoſt, and conſequently vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Scripture as rightly as <hi>M. John Caluin,</hi> &amp; yet this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Doctour, and great Saint writeth theſe very words which I do moſt faithfully tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate out of him: <hi>By the prayers of the holy Church
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42934:11"/>
and the wholſome ſacrifice, and by the almes which are giuen for their ſoules, it is not to be doubted, but the dead are holpen, that they may be dealt withall more mercyfully by our Lord, then their ſins haue deſerued; for this deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from our Fathers, the vniuerſall Church doth obſerue, that for thoſe who are dead in the Communion of the body &amp; bloud of Christ, Prayer should be made, when in the Sacrifice it ſelfe they in their place are remembred; and that, that Sacrifice should be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred to be offered vp for them. But when works of mercy are offered vp for their ſakes, who can doubt but that they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile them, for whom prayers are not in vaine offered vp to God? It is not to be doubted in any caſe, but that theſe things do profit the dead. Serm.</hi> 32. <hi>de verb. Apost.</hi> Thus writeth S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin,</hi> repeating ouer &amp; ouer againe in ſo few lines; <hi>It is not to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; who can doubt; It is not to be doubted in any caſe, that theſe things do profit the Dead.</hi> This being ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42934:11"/>
cleare, all other authorityes may ſeeme ſuperfluous. He who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth more teſtimonyes may read in <hi>Bellarmine (de Purgatorio)</hi> the words of <hi>S. Athanaſius, Baſil, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen, Cyril, Chryſostome, Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Cyprian, Ambroſe, Hierome</hi> &amp; others: we alſo ſhall haue frequent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to cite many other places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Purgatory proued by Reaſon grounded in Scripture.</head>
               <p n="1">1. AS it is a great Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Atheiſts who deny a God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder of good &amp; puniſher of euil, that all the world but they ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledge ſuch a God: ſo it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but be a ſtrong argument againſt Proteſtants, who deny <hi>Purgatory,</hi> that all Heathens, Iewes, Turkes, and all ciuill nations do vſe Prayer for the dead. The reaſon why all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42934:12"/>
agree ſo vniuerſally in this point, muſt needs be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the light of naturall Reaſon; which as it tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that there be ſome men ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good, who deſerue nothing but reward, others very bad who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue nothing but puniſhment; ſo it teacheth, that there is a third kind of men, who with the good they do worthy of reward, do alſo ſome ill, worthy of ſome (though not eternall) puniſhment; &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently it will belong to higher Powers to giue theſe men due cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſment: which as we ſee they eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape often in this life, it muſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be giuen them in the next. S. <hi>Austin</hi> thought this to be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that he ſaith <hi>in Euchir. c.</hi> 109. <hi>Jt is not to be denyed, but that the ſoules of thoſe who are departed, are much relieued by the pitty of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing friends, when either the Sacrifice of our Mediator is offered for them, or Almes are giuen in the Church, in their behalf; becauſe there is a certain
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42934:12"/>
state of life neither ſo good, but that they may haue need of theſe helps af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death, nor yet ſo euill, but that theſe offices may profit them. And on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, there is another state of men ſo good, that they need not this help, and of others ſo euill, that they cannot be helped by it when they are dead. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heere in this life all merit is gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby after this life a man may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued, or not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The anſwer which Proteſtants vſe to make is very weake; for they ſay, that although ſome men liue ſo that they do not deſerue Hell, and yet liue not ſo well but they deſerue ſome puniſhment; yet theſe men, ſay they, ſhall not go to <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> but by the onely vndergo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the paines of death, they ſhall be ſufficiently puniſhed for their ſinnes. This anſwere for two reaſons is apparently falſe. Firſt for that the vndergoing of death, is a puniſhment due vnto all men for originall ſinne; <hi>For</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Paul
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42934:13"/>
Rom.</hi> 5.) <hi>by one man ſinne entred into the world, and by ſinne death, and ſo vnto all men death did paſſe,</hi> euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſucking babes, who for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe vndergoe this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Secondly we ſee the paines of death equally ſhared among the good and bad: and in the floud of <hi>Noë</hi> all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffered the ſame death of being drowned, &amp; yet the ſinnes of many were moſt vnequall.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This proofe drawne from natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Reaſon is exceedingly illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and confirmed by three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples certaine in holy Scripture. The firſt is, that there are ſome ſins only veniall, and not lyable to eternall torments, and yet lyable to ſome torments. <hi>That ſeruant</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Luke cap.</hi> 22.) <hi>who knoweth the will of his Lord, and doth not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, shall be beaten with many stripes: but he that knoweth it not, and doth things worthy of stripes, shall be beaten with few stripes.</hi> Hence it is euident, that there be ſome
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42934:13"/>
men who do things worthy of ſtripes, which they ſhall not eſcape, but yet <hi>they shall be beaten with few stripes.</hi> But if theſe ſtripes be to be layd on for all Eternity (as all ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes be, which are payd in hell) they will not be few; becauſe being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting, the number of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will be without number: will any one call theſe ſtripes few? Or can any man perſwade himſelf, that a God, who is all mercy, will in this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull manner puniſh the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of one idle word? yet Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, that we ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable <hi>for euery idle word we ſpeake. Matth.</hi> 12. Wherefore we muſt be lyable to ſome puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for euery idle word; ſo that if a man of full age conuerted from i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry be baptized, and by and by after killed, before he commit any other ſinne then the ſpeaking of one idle word onely; ſhall this man be tormented for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſo long as God ſhall be God?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42934:14"/>
And ſhall the Father of mercyes giue this vnmercifull ſentence? Doubtleſſe if any man can do a thing worthy of ſtripes, &amp; for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it deſerue only to be beaten with few ſtripes, this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may hope for this mercy: but for greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this he cannot hope, ſeeing that Chriſt ſaith that ſome accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is to be giuen for that idle word. Some puniſhment therefore he muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, but not eternall, &amp; conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly not in hell, but in <hi>Purgatory</hi> for he muſt be beaten with few ſtripes, not with many, or euerlaſting ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The ſecond Principle is taught vs in the Apocalips <hi>cap.</hi> 21. to wit, That nothing defyled ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen: &amp; conſequently a man defiled with one onely idle word, and ſo dying ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of heauen, vntill he be cleanſed in <hi>Purgatory-fyre;</hi> For, <hi>he who buildeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tuble vpon the foundation shall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42934:14"/>
yet ſo as by fyre,</hi> ſaith S. Paul 1. <hi>Cor. 3. But</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Ambroſe) wheras S. Paul ſaith, yet ſo as by fyre, he sheweth indeed, that he shall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but yet shall ſuffer the punishment of fyre; that being purged by fyre, he may be ſaued and not tormented for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, as the Jnfidels are with euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fyre. Serm.</hi> 20. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 118. Moſt agreeable to this doctrine be the words of our Sauiour: <hi>Be at agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with thy Aduerſary betyme whilst thou art in the way with him, least per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps thou be caſt into priſon: Amen, I ſay vnto thee, thou shalt not go out from thence, till thou repayest the last farthing. Matth.</hi> 5. That is, vntill thou ſhalt haue made ſatisfaction for euery one of thy leaſt ſins, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> who telleth vs: <hi>This is that which he ſayth: Thou shalt not go out of priſon, vntill thou shalt pay, euen to thy little ſinnes. In c.</hi> 5. <hi>Matth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The third Principle is, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our ſins both mortall and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42934:15"/>
veniall be forgiuen vs, whenſoeuer we are truly penitent for them; yet all the paine due to theſe our ſins, is not always forgiuen, togeather with the ſins. This may be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by many examples in the Scripture. For breuity ſake I will ſpecify only two. The firſt it this: Originall ſinne is forgiuen vs by baptiſme, &amp; yet the paines which are inflicted for originall ſinne, be not wholy taken away by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, but euen thoſe innocent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, vnto whom by baptiſme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal ſinne was forgiuen, do ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the puniſhment of death due vnto them, for no other cauſe, but for that very originall ſinne, which was forgiuen them by baptiſme; for that, I ſay, they endure death: becauſe, <hi>by one man ſinne entred into the world, and by ſinne death, and ſo vnto all men</hi> (euen vnto innocents) <hi>death did paſſe. Rom.</hi> 5. The ſecond example is this: <hi>Dauid</hi> did ſo truly repent him of his ſinne of adultery
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42934:15"/>
&amp; murther, that God told him by the Prophet <hi>Nathan: Our Lord hath taken away thy ſinne.</hi> 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold heere the ſinnes of <hi>Dauid</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, and yet preſently God tels him: <hi>Neuertheleſſe, becauſe thou hast made the enemyes of the Lord to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme, for this thing the ſonne which is borne vnto thee dying, shall dye.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold heere a puniſhment inflicted vpon <hi>Dauid, euen for this thing,</hi> for which God had pardoned him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Out of this Principle it clearly followeth that there is a <hi>Purgatory.</hi> For ſeing that (as we haue proued) there remaineth many tymes ſome puniſhment due to the ſinne which is forgiuen; and ſeing that a man may dye before he hath ſuffered this puniſhment due by iuſtice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; it doth neceſſarily follow that this puniſhment muſt be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him in the world to come: not in hell, becauſe the ſinne is forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, but yet in the priſon of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, <hi>out of which he shall not goe,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42934:16"/>
vntill he hath payd the last farthing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. But heere it may be demanded, how this doctrine agrees with the ſaying of God: <hi>When the wicked ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> shall be conuerted from his impiety, I will not remember his iniquities. Ezech.</hi> 18. I anſwere, that God is ſaid not to remember them in his wrath &amp; vengance, by remitting the eternal paine due vnto them. So he did not remember the ſinne of <hi>Dauid,</hi> but <hi>did take it away from him:</hi> yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, <hi>for this thing,</hi> he took from him, by an vntimely death, his ſonne, whoſe life he begged ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly. The matter may fitly be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by this ſimilitude. If a man ſhould owe me a millio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of pounds, &amp; ſhould beg of me to forgiue the debt, I might be moſt truly ſaid to grant his requeſt, though I ſhould forgiue the debt on this conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he ſhould pay me only twenty ſhillings, as it were for a fine. Now we know our ſinnes be our debts: for one mortall ſinne only a man is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42934:16"/>
lyable to euerlaſting torments; but if this man being truly penitent, beggeth pardon of this his ſinne, God is ſo mercifull that he will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue and forget it; yet withall he is ſo iuſt, that in place of it he will impoſe ſome ſmall fine, as I may ſay, though this fine be far ſmaller then twenty ſhillings in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a million of pounds; for one pound a million of times doubled will come to be a million: but a Purgatory, euen of a million of yeares, though it ſhould be neuer ſo often doubled or redoubled can neuer come to make a ſumme of yeares equall to the yeares contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Eternity of paines, due to this ſinne, before it was forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. This I haue ſet downe at large, that all may ſee how merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully God doth deale with vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for one act of true pennance he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeth an Eternity of paines, into the temporall puniſhment of ſome yeares in <hi>Purgatory:</hi> for this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42934:17"/>
ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be but a great mercy, thogh this Purgatory were to laſt neuer ſo many yeares in number, becauſe the yeares of Eternity be without number.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The firſt Motiue to pray for the Soules in Purgatory which is, The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſenſible Paines they ſuffer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. NAture doth teach vs, that the moſt forcible Eloquence to mooue compaſſion is that, which ſetteth forth the greatnes of our miſery. The miſeryes which theſe poore ſoules ſuffer are reduced to two. The one <hi>Paena ſenſus,</hi> which is the ſenſible paine they feele cauſed by the exceſſiue bitternes of their torments. The other is called <hi>Paena damni,</hi> which is that inexplicable anguiſh of mind and grief ariſing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42934:17"/>
from the liuely apprehenſion of the loſſe of God, which for a tyme they are to ſuſtaine. To which we may add the long continuance of their torments. From theſe three we will draw the motiues, which (if they be well pondered) may make the hardeſt Pharao-like hart in the world to take ſome compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on theſe poore ſoules.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The firſt Motiue then, is the greatnes of that ſenſible paine, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the exceſſiue ſharpnes of theſe torments. How great &amp; how bitter the torments be, ſpeaking of that which hapneth for the moſt part, and not of that which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times may happen to ſome few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Soules, (whoſe ſins were ſmall and whoſe pennance great) how great I ſay theſe torments be, ſpeaking of them as they are for the moſt part, may be ſhewed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Firſt becauſe the torments of <hi>Purgatory</hi> exceed all euen the very greateſt torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of this life. <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:42934:18"/>
vpon thes words of S. Paul, <hi>but yet they shal be ſaued as by fyre,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>Becauſe S. Paul doth ſay that theſe men shall be ſaued by fyre, therfore this fyre is contemned: but ſurely although they shall be ſaued by it, yet this fyre is more grieuous then whatſoeuer a man can ſuffer in this life, albeit you know how great &amp; how intolerable things men haue ſuffered or may ſuffer.</hi> And, <hi>l. de vera &amp; falſa pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. c.</hi> 18. the ſame <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſaith: <hi>This fyre, I tell you, though it be not euerlasting yet it is paſſing grieuous, for it doth far paſſe all paines that any man can ſuffer in this life; neuer was there yet found out ſo great a paine in flesh as that is, though Martyrs haue ſuffered strange torments, and many malefactors exceeding great punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Againe, the ſame holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maketh vs a very excellent &amp; neceſſary exhortation out of this his ſo often deliuered doctrine. <hi>Some men</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vſe to ſay, J care not greatly how long I ſtay in this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42934:18"/>
fyre, ſeing that at last, I shall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to life euerlasting: But (alas) deare Brother, let no man ſay thus, becauſe this Purgatory fyre is more sharp, then any punishment which in this life can be ſeene, imagined, or felt. He that now will be loath to put one of his fingars into burning fyre, ought to feare the torment of that fyre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Other holy Doctours haue had the like feeling of this matter. The great <hi>S. Gregory</hi> writeth thus, <hi>in</hi> 3. <hi>Pſal. paenit. I know that after this life ſome must be cleanſed by purging fire, and others muſt receaue ſentence of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation; but becauſe I eſteeme that purging fire, though it be tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, to be more intollerable then all the tribulation that in this life can be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, I greatly feare to be purged in the wrath of tranſitory vengeance.</hi> And Venerable <hi>Bede, in eund. Pſal.</hi> affirmeth, <hi>That no torture either of martyrs, or malefactours can be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the paines of Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Secondly, it is an opinion not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42934:19"/>
improbable that the very leaſt tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Purgatory doth ſurpaſſe the very greateſt in this world. Of this opinion is our learned <hi>S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme,</hi> who <hi>(in Elucidat.)</hi> ſpeaking of theſe torments ſaith: <hi>De quibus, minimum maius est quàm maximum, quod in hac. vita excogitari potest:</hi> of the which the leaſt is bigger then the biggeſt, which in this life can be deuiſed. Amongſt the Epiſtles of <hi>S. Austin</hi> there is one, which ſome thinke <hi>S. Cyril</hi> to haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, in which there be theſe moſt fearfull words: <hi>There is not a man liuing who had not rather be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all the paines and torments together, which all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world from Adam vntill this time haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, then be for one day tormented with the least paine which is either in Hell or Purgatory. Epist.</hi> 206. Yea <hi>S. Thomas</hi> prince of the Deuines, doth proue this to be moſt true <hi>in</hi> 4. <hi>d.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>J.</hi> 1. <hi>a.</hi> 2. becauſe there is not one in Purgatory, who during the time
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42934:19"/>
he is there, is not depriued of the ſight of God, &amp; that for his owne fault. Now the ſuffering of this baniſhment culpably, is a paine greater then all the paines of the world are, or can be. Out of which diſcourſe it followes that there is not any one in Purgatory, who doth not euery inſtant that he is there ſuffer more then is or can be ſuffered in this world, though all myſeries ſhould meet in one. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may be of a contrary opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but their opinion may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps more contrary to truth.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Thirdly it is an opinion moſt commonly receaued amongſt the greateſt Deuines, that the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Purgatory for the time they laſt be as grieuous as the torments of Hell. <hi>The paines of Hell and Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory be of one greatnes, but thoſe of Hell expect no end, thoſe of Purgatory haue an end,</hi> ſayth the author of the Epiſtle which now we cited out of <hi>S. Auſtin.</hi> And <hi>Denys</hi> the <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:42934:20"/>
is much of the ſame opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>l. de iud. anim.</hi> Theſe opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s I thought good to ſet downe, not as if they were articles of faith (for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were not opinions) but to the end we may ſee, what feeling theſe great Saints &amp; Doctours of Gods Church haue had of this point. And I adde,</p>
               <p n="7">7. Fourthly, that reaſon it ſelfe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by Faith doth conuince theſe torments to be exceeding great, becauſe theſe Soules though they be ſaued, yet <hi>are they ſaued, ſo as by fire.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. Now, of all the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which can be ſuffered none is more painfull then thoſe of fire, and perhaps all the other tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which our world hath, can ſcarce ſo bitterly torture a poore creature, as it would be tortured, if it were poſſibly for it to be kept without conſuming in the midſt of the mercileſſe flames of a glaſſe-furnace, the fire of which would ſoone as it were penetrate it ſelfe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42934:20"/>
with the very in moſt parts of that afflicted wretch; his bones would glow like red hoat bars of iron, his marrow would ſcorch him more fiercely then melted lead, his bloud would boyle more furiouſly then high-ſeething oyle, his nayles, his teeth, his griſſes, his very skull would be like plates of bright fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming braſſe all on burning fire. But alas! deare Brother, there be many differences betweene our hoateſt fire &amp; the ſcorching flames of Purgatory. Our fire was created by God meerly for our comfort and commodity: that fire is made for no other end, then to afflict, paine, and torment thoſe guilty Soules. Our fire by being out of the proper ſphere, by being min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with groſſer and duller ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary qualityes which be round about it, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety which it findeth in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry matter it feedeth on, hath the natiue force, actiuity, &amp; fiercenes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42934:21"/>
much abated. That fire hath not one of theſe hinderances, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſeth continually in the higheſt degree all the force of natiue fury. In fine, our fire in compariſon of that fire, by holy Doctors, &amp; nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by our worthy Countrey-man Syr <hi>Thomas More</hi> in the end of his rare worke called, <hi>The ſupplication of the Soule,</hi> is ſtyled, &amp; eſteemed a kind of <hi>painted fire rather then true fire.</hi> Theſe conſiderations made the deuout <hi>S. Bernard</hi> break into theſe patheticall words: <hi>O would to God ſome man would now before hand pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for my head abundance of water, and to my eyes a fountaine of teares, for ſo perhaps the burning fire would take no hould, where running teares had clenſed before. de</hi> 6. <hi>tribul.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 55. <hi>in Cant</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Two other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderations may be added vnto theſe; the one is the cauſe why theſe torments are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, which is the making of due ſatisfaction for ſinne, which thogh
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42934:21"/>
it be but veniall, yet being that it is an offence of God, is a thing ſo deteſtable, that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted either for the gayning of ten thouſand worlds, or the auoyding of the greateſt euill poſſible: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the goodnes of God is not to be violated and diſpleaſed, his ſacred maieſty is not the leaſt to be diſhonoured (being that it is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne and infinit) for the good of any inferior creature, that is, or may be. Wherfore the ſo light co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſo many veniall ſins as men daily &amp; hourly commit, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expiated but by puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a higher rank then we can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. And this is the reaſon why the learnedſt Doctors &amp; holieſt Saints, who had moſt light of Gods great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, had alſo greateſt feeling of the paines due to euery litle offence of ſo infinit a Nature: and this is the reaſon why they, whoſe vnderſtad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings are either clouded with na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ignorance, or obſcured with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42934:22"/>
ſinfull affections, or wholy dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with hereſy, are as dul in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending theſe paines, as they are blockiſh in framing a worthy conceit of Gods infinit goodnes and ſupreme Soueraingty.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The other thing heere conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is, that the day of mercy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with the day of our life, we are after to expect nothing els but iuſtice, and therfore our Sauiour doth verily ſay vnto vs, that we ſhal not go out of this priſon, <hi>vntill we haue payd the last farthing. Math.</hi> 5. Which is a terrible co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration if we haue a due feeling of our debts; whereunto what we are to ſay in the fifth Chapter, will exceedingly help. Neither can Proteſtants be ſcandalized at what hath heere bin ſaid, if they remember, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto their faith, all ſins are mortall, and therefore deſerue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting paines.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Wel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, theſe diſtreſſed ſoules ſuffering ſuch things as none who
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42934:22"/>
hath the hart of a man, could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to ſee a dog ſuffer if he could eaſe him; and theſe ſoules being the ſoules of our Bretheren, the ſoules of Chriſts Bretheren, the ſoules which he loued ſo dearely, that he moſt ioyfull ſpent the very laſt drop of bloud in his body for their ſakes; how can we thus ſlight their complaints with a deafe eare. O if we were in this pittifull caſe, how hoatly ſhould we cite thoſe words of our Sauiour, that voice, that outery of nature her ſelfe: <hi>All that you would that men should do for you, do alſo for them. Matth.</hi> 7. <hi>Denis</hi> the <hi>Carthaſian</hi> relateth the words of one, who by diuine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation was admitted to ſee theſe torments, &amp; indeed they be worth relating. <hi>God is my witnes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that if I did ſee any man, though this man had as cruelly, as man could, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſuſed, tortured, or killed my deareſt friends, and had done me all the miſchiefe, which one man could
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42934:23"/>
do to another; yet if J did ſe this man condemned to ſuch paines as there</hi> (in Purgatory) <hi>I beheld, I would a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, if it could be done, ſuffer death for his deliuery. l. de iudic. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim. art.</hi> 23. Such force hath this Conſideration liuely apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV:</hi> The ſecond Motiue, drawne from the intolerable paines the ſoules ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, by being banished from the ſight of God.</head>
               <p n="1">1. TO vnderſtand how great a paine it is to be baniſhed, though but for a time, from the face of God, is a thing wholy impoſſible, vntill we come to know, what an infinit good it is to poſſeſſe God, but we may haue ſome little ſcantling of it by theſe conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The firſt Conſideration: All the ioy, pleaſure, dainties, riches, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42934:23"/>
honours of this world, yea and of a million of worlds, though they were a million of times more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then this world is, and all this ioy &amp; happines were eternall; yet all this put togeather, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed as perfectly as might be, is a thing no wayes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable to that happines which the poſſeſſion of God for one onely moment doth bring with it; ſo that to be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of this poſſeſſion, debarred of this happines, reſtrayned of this Bliſſe (when we are in an eſtate ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of it, &amp; requiring it) is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery without all compariſon grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ſhould be the loſſe of all the riches, honours, and pleaſures which the eternall poſſeſſion of a million of worlds, a million of ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes more pleaſant then our world could affoard. What griefe then muſt the loſſe of this good, cauſe in a ſoule that knoweth her loſſe?</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſecond Conſideration. All the torments of this world though
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42934:24"/>
they were a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d times greater, ought according to right reaſon to be ioyfully ſuffered, if by the ſuffering of them altogether, we might be able to purchaſe the ſight of God but for one moment: for to ſee God is ſuch a good, that it would ſeeme cheape bought with all thoſe euills, his ſight being a good of a far higher order the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any euill can be an euill. Hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that the ſuffering (though but for a moment) the loſſe of this good, is a miſery inconceptible. How cleare is this, and yet how litle vnderſtood?</p>
               <p n="4">4. The third Conſideration may be taken from the liuely &amp; cleare manner with which theſe ſoules haue their whole mind and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion faſt bent both night and day vpon the greatnes of this their ſo infinit a loſſe. We know by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that in matter of paine, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, and miſery, nothing tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wholy to giue our
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42934:24"/>
ſelues ouer, or rather to be carryed by the violence of them, to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall conſideration of the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of our afflictions. All other comforts which may be thought on, for the eaſe of thoſe deſolate Soules, are no more then inough to keep their mindes in a perfect patience amidſt a world of ſo great miſeryes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fourth Conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ſoules do moſt perfectly loue God, &amp; they do penetrate, in a far per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecter manner then they could do in this life, the reaſons (which are all moſt forcible) mouing to loue that infinite Goodnes. Wherfore ſeing themſelues on the one ſide in an eſtate capable of enioying God, and on the other debarred of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying him (whome they loue ſo affectionatly, that it is a death to be ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him) their minds are as it were torne aſunder on the rack of loue. <hi>Loue</hi> (ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.) <hi>is as stronge as death,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42934:25"/>
and emulation as hard as hell, the torches of it be torches of fire &amp; flames, many waters cannot quench it neyther can riuers ouerwhelme it &amp;c.</hi> Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this world where we haue ſo little knowledge of God in our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, &amp; where we follow this knowledge ſo faintly with our wils; ſome choice ſeruants of God ſuffer ſtrange things in this kind through the abſence of their belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, though as yet they are not in an eſtate fit to enioy him. Father <hi>Baptista Sanctius</hi> of the Society of Ieſus, was one of theſe; For when he manifeſted his conſcience vnto his Superiour, he profeſſed he was really of opinion, that very griefe would kill him out of hand, if he ſhould come to know for certayne that his life ſhould be prolonged for the ſpace but of one whol day: ſo truly ſtrong as death was that loue which inflamed his heart to the enioying of his beloued. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dou. de Ponte in vita P. Baltaſ. c.</hi> 17.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42934:25"/>
Few can belieue, and fewer can vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this; but thoſe who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed loue God, ſee it with their eyes. If the ruthefull moanes of ſuch true louers deſerue not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, there is no ſuch thing, as they call Mercy, in the world.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The fift Conſideration. Theſe ſoules know they are depriued of this infinit good (which they ſo ardently loue) for no other cauſe but their owne fault, their owne careleſſy committed ſinnes, ſinnes which did offend and affront this infinit goodnes, which now they loue ſo tenderly. And this it is which cutteth, as deep as the ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt edge of grief can cut into the ſofteſt heart which weepeth with teares of blood as ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it thinks (and it can neuer ceaſe from thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king) that it was not only a trifle which ſeparated it in this manner from God, but a wickednes abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in his ſight, an offence of ſuch an Excellency, a contempt of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42934:26"/>
ſuch a Maieſty, a diſpleaſure of ſuch a Goodnes, an ingratitude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch a Benefactour. All this it is that goeth to their very heart, this all the powers of their Soules bewaile, and lament to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their power, with teares which neither can nor will admit of comfort, vntill due ſatisfaction be made euen to the leaſt, and laſt farthing.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The ſixt and laſt Conſideration differeth in this from the former, that as thoſe ſoules are tormented with ſuch vnſpeakable grief whilſt they ponder the miſeries of this baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for their owne offences as they are diſpleaſing to him who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſo purely loue; ſo they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo put on a new torture, when out of naturall loue vnto themſelues (which now well-ordered charity doth much increaſe) they attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely conſider and deeply penetrate what it is to be depriued of ſuch a good, ſuch a ioy, ſuch a bliſſe, for
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42934:26"/>
ſuch a ſmall, ſuch a no good, ſuch a miſchieuous euill as they ſinned for, a pleaſure ſo vaine, ſo ſhort, ſo vgly, ſo irrationall, and ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to their ſoules, and yet (to vſe their language) ſuch was my folly (ah wretch, not only miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but mad) as to forgo euen ſuch a good, for ſuch a bare, ſuch a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefull, ſuch a peſtiferous trifle as that was: ſo many degrees of glory which would haue made me ſo happy for all eternity, are wholly and irrecouerably loſt for a pure (ah moſt impure) nothing! How ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was I inſpired to do this thing and yet &amp;c. Theſe &amp; far more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable then theſe be the anguiſhes of thoſe ſoules, far greater then eyther thoſe of Eſau ſelling his inheritance for a meſſe of potage, or thoſe of Adam for making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Paradiſe for the taſte of an apple, or any other this world euer had, or ſhall haue.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Summe vp now in thy mind all
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42934:27"/>
theſe conſiderations together, and thinke, in what a ſea of ſorrowes that heart muſt bee, into which day and night ſo great &amp; ſo many flouds do vnlade their waues, and yet canſt thou not find in thy hart to affoard them ſome ſmall reliefe? <hi>He</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. John cap. 1.</hi>3.) <hi>who poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſseth the ſubstance of this world, and shall ſee his brother to haue neceſſity, and shutteth his bowels from him, how doth the Charity of God remaine in this man?</hi> He ſaith not, how doth the charity towards his neighbour but how doth the Charity of God remaine in him? And if thou whoſoeuer thou art, thus ſhutteſt thy bowels in a neceſſity, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme almoſt as a neceſſity can be, of thy owne and Chriſts brother, I am ſure that the charity of thy neighbour hath no place in thee: but as for charity towards God, it is not I, but S. Iohn, who doth as it were denying aske, <hi>how doth the charity of God remaine in thee?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:42934:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The third Motiue taken from the long time that theſe Paines do indure.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IF theſe paines were to be ended in a ſhort ſpace, our hard-hartednes might the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſome excuſe: but (ſpeaking ſtil of what happeneth for the moſt part) it is a thing ſcarce to be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bted of, that they continue very long: for the holy Church is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to keepe the Anniuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of thoſe who dyed a hundred, or two hundred yeares ago. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it appeareth, that there is reaſon to feare that many haue a long ſtay in Purgatory. The learned <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine l.</hi> 2. <hi>de gemit. columb. cap.</hi> 2. doth recount ſome hiſtories very au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall (as he excellently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth) out of which it appeareth that diuers ſoules are condemned
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42934:28"/>
to Purgatory euen till the day of Iudgement. And <hi>Tertullian,</hi> one of the ancienteſt fathers, ſpeaking of theſe paines of Purgatory ſaith, <hi>Thou shalt not depart perhaps vntill the day of thy Reſurrection. lib. de ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma c.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now, if we require why God doth hould this manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in rather deteyning vs long time in our puniſhments, then in adding to the bitternes of our tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that which is taken out in length of time; we can deuiſe no other reaſon, then that our ſinnes haue deſerued this miſery alſo, and men would litle apprehend to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all that could be ſuffered in one moment, if the next moment they were to be eternally happy; and therefore God, who in his ſeuere iudgement had a mercifull regard to that which would worke moſt with our dull apprehenſions, did ordaine that (as S. Auguſtin ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aketh, <hi>hom.</hi> 15. <hi>ex.</hi> 50. <hi>hom.) Quanta
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42934:28"/>
fuerit peccati materia, tanta eſſet tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcunti mora;</hi> ſo great as the matter of our ſinnes ſhall haue bin, ſo long ſhould be the ſtay of our paſſage. The beſt way therfore to make vs haue ſome conceit of the long co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of theſe paines, is to ſee how great the matter vſes to be on which they feed; that is, what a kind of quantity the ſinnes of men vſe moſt commonly to amount vnto.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A little Arithmaticke will giue vs a great inſight in this matter. The iuſt man is ſaid <hi>to ſinne ſeuen ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes a day:</hi> wherfore we may eaſily allow thrice more a day to one of thoſe whom we call good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men, ſuch as the world hath but few of: ſuch a man therfore as this is, doth ſinne (venially) ten times a day, taking one day with another. The dayes in a whole yeare are three hundred ſixty fiue, wherefore he who euery day ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ten times, muſt at the yeares
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42934:29"/>
end haue ſinned ten times as often as there be dayes in a yeare; which ſumme is eaſily found out by only putting one cypher to the number of the dayes in the yeare, which are 365. add now one cypher &amp; we ſhall haue 3650. So that the ſinnes of this good man, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in one yeare come to no leſſe, then three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred and fifty. But if this honeſt man ſhould liue euen in this good manner ten yeares, he ſhould at ten yeares end haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the former ſumme ten ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, becauſe he doth double it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery yeare, which ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me alſo is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily had by adding one cypher to the former ſumme of 3650. which if we doe, we do find 36500. What a thing is this? An innocent man, not a man but a youth doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thirty ſix thouſand and fiue hundred ſinnes all in ten yeares; wherfore if the youth ſhould for ten yeares more continue this his vertuous courſe of life, he would
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42934:29"/>
double the ſinnes of his former life, and make them amount to ſeuenty three thouſand, before he came to be a middle aged man. O, ſaith S. Auguſtine, perhaps when thou doſt conſider a little ſinne a part, &amp; by it ſelfe, thou doſt ſlight it; yet ſaith he, <hi>ſi comtemnis quando appendis, expaueſce quando numeras: Jf thou contemnest thy little ſinnes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou doſt weigh them; yet tremble when thou dost number them. in epist. Joan. tract. 1.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Let vs reflect now a little, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we go any further, what a kind of Purgatory this man, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not fully of midle age, a man very pious, a man who neuer commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one mortall ſinne, would be lyable vnto, if he ſhould dy at this age: for perhaps of thoſe ſeuenty three thouſand ſinnes, he hath not fully ſatisfyed for the odd three thouſand; or if he hath, he hath done more then moſt men vſe to doe: for of all miſeryes one of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42934:30"/>
greateſt is, that thoſe who ſinne moſt, haue leaſt care to ſatisfy for their ſinnes: now what a Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thinke you, ſeuenty thouſand ſinnes will deſerue? <hi>Thy iudgments</hi> (O God) <hi>are a deep bottomles pit! Pſal.</hi> 35.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But why put we a caſe which ſo ſeldome happens? The ordinary courſe of men is to commit many and enormous mortall ſinnes, and veniall without all ſcruple, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently without all number; yea many hould on this ſtraine vntill they come to be very old, &amp; vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by reaſon of their yeares, &amp; vnwilling by reaſon of their ill ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits to do any Pennance, and ſo they content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſome few houres to deplore and confeſſe thoſe ſinnes, which amount to far more thouſands, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there be minutes in the houres which they ſpend in lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Conſider now how vnſufficiently the grief of one minute is to cancel
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42934:30"/>
out all the paines due to a whole thouſand of ſinnes, and many of them very enormous.</p>
               <p n="6">6. There is alſo another thing in this reckoning to be much refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted on: that he, who ſhould haue but one only mortall ſinne, would be lyable after the forgiuenes of it, to a puniſhment far different (&amp; God know's how far) from that which he is lyable vnto who hath only veniall ſinnes to ſatisfy for, though their number be exceeding great; for if one mortall ſinne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be forgiuen, be lyable vnto an eternity of puniſhment, &amp; moſt bitter puniſhment, &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuch a puniſhment, as all the veniall ſinnes a man can commit, would neuer deſerue the hundreth thouſand part of it; I will leaue it to a right valuing iudgement to eſteeme how much more paine God is like to impoſe vpon him who hath this one forgiuen mortall ſinne to ſatisfy for, then
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42934:31"/>
on him, who hath onely veniall ſinnes, and thoſe alſo forgiuen, to ſatisfy for, though the number of them ſhould be exceeding great. Well then, if one mortall ſinne bringeth with it ſuch a dreadfull Purgatory, how are they like to be dealt withall, who euery day run vpon the ſcore, &amp; thus conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue not for many dayes, but years together, during which time they being alwayes in ſinne neuer make ſatisfaction for the leaſt they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. If holy Dauid ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. <hi>My iniquityes haue layd hold on me, J was not able to ſee them</hi> (they were ſo many,) <hi>for they were multiplyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the hayres of my head;</hi> what may theſe men (<hi>who drinke vp iniquity like water, Iob.</hi> 15.) think of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of their ſinnes, who perhaps haue a hundred for <hi>Dauids</hi> one? Such like conſiderations as theſe made the deuout <hi>S. Bouaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture</hi> cry out; <hi>I haue ſinned aboue the number of the ſands of the ſea. How then shall
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42934:31"/>
J number that which is without num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? How shall I ſuffice when I shalbe inforced to pay my debt to the very last farthing? S. Bonau. in paruo bono.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. But let vs marke a litle what ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction is vſually made by thoſe that ſtand in ſo great need of it. The ordinary wayes to ſatisfy be theſe, Faſting, Prayer, &amp; Almeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds, and ſometimes by Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences; and all theſe things muſt be done in the ſtate of Grace, in which theſe men are ſeldome long togeather, and therefore moſt of theſe workes (of which they doe ſo few) come wholy to be loſt: but when they are not thus caſt away, let vs ſee what they will come to. As for faſting, when it cannot be ſhifted of by any pretence, faſt they do, but God, knowes how many times they looſe, eyther the whole or the greater part of this good worke: for they haue ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions to ſweete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their faſts with ſuch variety of dainty diſhes, that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42934:32"/>
it is much to be feared, leaſt in place of ſatisfying for their old ſinnes, they commit new ſinnes of gluttony, which require a new ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. Now for prayer it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly performed by them with ſo many diſtractions, irreuerences, and other imperfections, that the world may ſeeme not to goe amiſſe if there be inough of their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers made ſo well that it may ſuffice to make due recompence for that which is made ſo ill. Almeſdeeds the poore cannot giue, &amp; the rich will not, for they do liue &amp; meane euer to liue, ſay what you will, at ſo high a rate, that they thinke they do a great matter, if they can get inough honeſtly to maintaine their brauery, &amp; to diſcharge their debts: For as for paying the debts they owe to God they are reſolued that he ſhalbe payed laſt. Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences indeed are one of the great mercys of God, which in how great need we ſtand of, any man of iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:42934:32"/>
will ſee clearly by this whole diſcours; but ſuch is eyther the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, or ſtrange careleſneſſe of moſt men (eſpecially of ſuch as haue moſt need) that perhaps the groſſe neglect of them, may well be reckoned for one of the chief cauſes, why many broyle ſo long in the flames of Purgatory.</p>
               <p n="8">8. It is now high time to end this diſcourſe, and I humbly &amp; earne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly beſeech the reader to take ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into his conſideration the poynts mentioned, as well for his owne ſpirituall profit, as for relief of his poore brethrens ſoules bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in Purgatory-flames, &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating to his Charity for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour: which if he do, I doubt not but he wilbe moued to compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and to a ſpeedy and liberall contribution of many ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good works.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:42934:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> That for the loue we beare to God, we ought to be much moued to help the Soulet in Purgatory.</head>
               <p n="1">1. HItherto we haue only treated of ſuch Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues as Charity towards our neighbour doth force vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: Now we will paſſe to the motiues which pure Charity towards God doth preſent vnto vs; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards we will come to thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, which well-ordered Charity towards our ſelues doth offer vs. To our preſent purpoſe then: A Soule which is enamored on Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and deſireth to pleaſe God in the higheſt manner, hath very many, and efficacious motiues to make her forward, to ayde the ſoules in Purgatory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The firſt motiue: God is of an excellency, worth, and perfection
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42934:33"/>
ſo infinite, that he deſerueth all poſſible loue, and honour. This conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maketh vs caſt about to ſee how we may procure, that this Excellency may be more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly loued &amp; glorified: wherfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that on earth we know him ſo imperfectly, and loue him ſo couldly, and glorify him ſo meanly; we reſt little ſatisfied with all which can be done by vs on earth; and ſo we ſeeke yet further, and conſider how perfectly God is knowne by the bleſſed in heauen, how they loue that Goodneſſe, how they glorify that Maieſty. Hence we burne with an ardent deſire, that God may in this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blime manner be more knowne, loued and honoured: &amp; then mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that it is in our power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure this, by obtaining the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſome ſoule, or ſoules out of Purgatory, which, being freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence by our meanes, would for euer and euer loue &amp; honour God
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42934:34"/>
in that moſt perfect manner; we bend our ſelues wholy to procure the deliuerance of theſe ſoules out of pure loue to Almighty God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſecond motiue. When we conſider our infinite obligations to God for his manifold benefits ſhowred down vpon vs, and being inflamed with a reſtleſſe deſire of ſhewing our ſelues truly gratefull, though wholy vnable, during the time of this mortall life, to thanke him as it is fitting; we vſe the beſt meanes we can deuiſe, to procure worthy thankes to be giuen him by ſome Soule, or Soules freed by our meanes, which both day and night may praiſe, extoll, &amp; thanke this diuine Goodneſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The third Motiue. When we conſider how great a Maieſty, how infinite a Goodneſſe, how great a benefactour we haue ſo often and ſo grieuouſly offended, we feele in our ſelues a ſtrong &amp; working de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of repayring this diſhonour
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42934:34"/>
done to that Maieſty, and cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling our owne ingratitude, by the greateſt honour we can inuent to procure; and therfore we imploy cheerfully our beſt good deeds in working the releaſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of as many ſoules as we can, that by their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall glorifying God, a perfecter recompence may be made for the diſhonour we haue done him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fourth Motiue is drawne out of the precedent put together, in this manner. God whoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency is ſo great, whoſe goodneſſe ſo infinite, whoſe benefits ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fold, whom I am obliged to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy for ſo many and ſo great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: this God, I ſay, taketh all that is done vnto his brethren for his ſake, as gratefully as if it were done vnto himſelfe; as Chriſt hath taught vs in plaine words, <hi>As long as you haue done theſe thinges to any one of my Brethren, you haue done them vnto me. Matth.</hi> 25. How can I then hould my ſelfe from vſing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42934:35"/>
any meanes, by which I may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme a thing as gratefull to my deare Lord, as if he had indured the exceſſiue torments of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and I had releaſed him? My Hart is hard, but I muſt confeſſe that this conſideration doth make it yield, and if there were no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but this, this alone might conuince all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> That, by offering our actions for the Soules in Purgatory, we purchaſe many great Commodities for our ſelues, and ſuſtaine no Jncommodity.</head>
               <p n="1">1. TO make this title good I will ſhew, that by this Deuotion we do not merit leſſe but more. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, that thus our actions are not leſſe but more impetratory. Thirdly, that thus we do not leſſe, but more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy for our ſinnes. Fourthly, that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42934:35"/>
thus we haue great hope to eſcape eyther all, or part of the paines of Purgatory. Fiftly, that thus we do nothing againſt Charity towards our ſelues; but that we ſhould do againſt the perfection of this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, if we ſhould not thus offer our actions for the ſoules in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. All theſe fiue points we will (by Gods grace) indeauour to make cleare in the next enſuing chapters, treating a part of euery one of them in order in a peculiar chapter; and that all which hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we are to ſay, may be better vnderſtood, we will ſpend this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Chapter in declaring how the buſines doth paſſe, when we offer any workes for the ſoules in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is therfore moſt diligently to be noted, as the ground of all we are to ſay, that our vertuous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may haue theſe three ſeuerall proprietyes together. They may be meritorious, they may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petratory,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:42934:36"/>
they may be ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. They are meritorious when they are good workes performed in the grace of God, hauing an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall reward promiſed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They are impetratory, for they do obtaine (<hi>beſides the crowne of iustice, which the iust iudge layeth vp for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the day of his coming.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim. 4</hi>) many other fauours beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them by the bountifull ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of our mercifull father: As for example, the life of our friend; as Dauid ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to obtaine, <hi>when he prayed and wept, and fasted a faſt, &amp; went in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and lay vpon the ground.</hi> 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12. to beg the life of his ſonne: Or the conuerſion of others, as the prayer made by <hi>S. Stephen</hi> did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of God the conuerſion of <hi>S. Paul. Act.</hi> 7. as <hi>S. Augustin</hi> teacheth; in fine, <hi>ask &amp; you shall haue. Luc.</hi> 11. Our good workes alſo are ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory, eyther alwayes (as many excellent Deuines hold) or (as all hold) if they be workes of any
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:42934:36"/>
labour, paine, or difficulty, as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, Prayer, and Almes-deeds; yea what good works are there, which our corrupted nature fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not difficulty in? Let vs ſee what foundation this ground of our diſcourſe hath in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That our good workes are me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious, is expreſly taught in the 6. of S. Matthew: and thoſe good workes are put by name, which make more for our purpoſe, to wit faſting, prayer &amp; Almeſdeeds the reward of which works we are there ſaid to looſe, if we do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blikly out of vanity; but if thou doeſt them in humble ſecrecy, <hi>Thy Father, who ſeeth thee in ſecret, will repay thee.</hi> And leaſt any man ſhould thinke, that only great workes ſhould be rewarded, our Sauiour in plaine tearmes doth tell vs, that he who giueth but a cup of cold water, ſhall not want his reward, if it be done for his ſake: &amp; we may
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:42934:37"/>
ſee how mindful our Lord is of his promlſe, for in the laſt iudgement day to thoſe, who ſhall haue done ſuch good workes as theſe are, he will ſay: <hi>Come you bleſſed of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poſſeſſe the kingdome prepared for you from the making of the world, for J was hungry, &amp; you gaue me to eate, thirsty and you gaue me to drinke. Matth.</hi> 25. Marke how God doth giue them heauen for the doing of good workes. <hi>Poſſeſſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the kingdome,</hi> for you gaue me to eate, to drinke &amp;c. And ſomewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ſame Chapter: <hi>Becauſe thou wert faithfull ouer a few things J will place thee ouer many; enter into the ioy of thy Lord.</hi> Marke this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, <hi>becauſe thou wert faithfull.</hi> This is the cauſe for which Chriſt ſaith, he giueth heauen. Let <hi>Luther,</hi> let <hi>Caluin,</hi> let thoſe who care for no good workes, name what other cauſe they pleaſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That our good Workes are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petratory, that is, haue vertue to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:42934:37"/>
mooue the liberality, goodneſſe, &amp; mercy of God, to beſtow, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of them, the grant of many fauours, when by prayer they are offered vp for this end (for if they be not thus offered vp, as they are ioyned and applyed to this end by prayer, perhaps not any good workes at all are impetratory, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting only prayer it ſelfe; &amp; not all prayer, but ſuch as containeth ſome petition:) That, I ſay, good workes are impetratory, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are thus ioyned with prayer, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently prooued out of that faſt of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who with the Prayer made for his ſonnes life, ioyned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo other workes of pennance, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the ground, faſting &amp;c. <hi>For the child,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>whilst he did yet liue, I did faſt &amp; weepe, but now ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is dead, why should I fast?</hi> 2. <hi>Reg. 12.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. That our good workes are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory, that is, that they (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and dignified by Grace
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:42934:38"/>
gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted through Chriſt his merits) haue vertue to cancell out ſin, and the paines due to ſin, is moſt cleare in Scripture; &amp; Heretikes (if loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to make ſatisfaction for their ſinnes did not blind them) cannot but ſee it. <hi>Almeſdeeds free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death:</hi> and <hi>Almeſ-deeds it is, which purgeth ſinne, and maketh vs find mercy, and life euerlasting. Tob.</hi> 12. <hi>Almeſ-deeds free from ſinne, and from death, and they do not ſuffer the ſoule to goe into darkneſſe. Tob.</hi> 4. <hi>Water quencheth the burning fier, and Almeſ-deeds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſinne. Eccl.</hi> 3. In the eleauenth Chapter of <hi>S. Luke</hi> our Sauiour ſpeaking to the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſaith, <hi>that they shall be condemned in the day of iudgment; that the bloud of all the Prophets ſlaine from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, shall be required at their hands:</hi> and ſix times one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another he pronounceth <hi>Woe</hi> againſt them; &amp; to thoſe vncleane men our Sauiour at the very ſame time ſaid: <hi>Neuertheleſſe, for that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:42934:38"/>
which remaineth giue Almes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all things are made cleane vnto you,</hi> as ſinfull people as you are. <hi>Wherfore let my counſell pleaſe thee</hi> (it is the moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t counſell of the Prophet <hi>Daniel) redeeme thy ſinnes with Almeſ-deeds, and thy iniquityes with the workes of mercy. Dan.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This being thus declared, it may eaſily be vnderſtood, how things do paſſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we offer vp any work for the ſoules in Purgatory. For firſt, the good worke thus offered vp is meritorious, and therfore we alwaies merit by it: neither can we giue this merit away, becauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is only due, &amp; Scripture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth it to thoſe only, who ſhall haue done well; wherfore we looſe not the leaſt parcell of the merit of our good workes, if we do them for the ſoules in Purgatory, yea we much increaſe it, as ſhal be ſhewed. Secondly, the good worke thus offered is impetratory, that is, it is apt to mooue Gods mercy to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42934:39"/>
graunt that fauour, for obtaining of which it is offered w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py death, peace among Chriſtians, the long and happy life of our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble King, or ſuch like things. Now the obtaining of all theſe requeſts is not the leaſt hindered, but very much (as we ſhall ſhew) furthered, though theſe workes, which we do, be giuen to the ſoules in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and offered vp to God for the ſatisfaction of the paines due vnto their ſinnes not fully ſatisfied for. Thirdly and laſtly, this good worke, which we offer for the ſoules in Purgatory, is ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and according to this ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory vertue which it hath (&amp; not as it is either meritorious or impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tratory) we do commonly apply it to the ſoules in Purgatory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the thing which theſe poore ſoules ſtand moſt in need of, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſatisfaction for their ſins not fully ſatisfied for: which ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction we make in their behalfe, as
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:42934:39"/>
holy <hi>Job</hi> did in behalfe of his ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, when he offered daily ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for their ſinnes. How this is not againſt Charity towards our ſelues, ſhall be declared hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> That by offering our actions for the Soules in Purgatory, we do not merit leſſe, but more.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat we do not merit leſſe, is euident out of the laſt Chapter: that we merit more then otherwiſe we ſhould haue done, if we had not applied theſe our actions to the ſoules in Purgatory, is taught by the Prince of Deuines <hi>S. Thomas l.</hi> 3. <hi>cont. Gentes c.</hi> 158. in theſe words: <hi>The affection of Charity in him who ſuffereth for his friend doth make his ſatisfaction more pleaſing to God, then if he had ſuffered for his owne ſelfe.</hi> And it is certaine out of holy
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:42934:40"/>
Scripture, that Charity doth adde an exceeding worth and value to our leaſt actions; for only Charity it is, which maketh a cup of <hi>cold water</hi> giuen for Chriſts ſake, to be rewarded in the life to come. And only Charity it was, which made the poore <hi>widdows mite</hi> of greater price, then the richeſt guifts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now then all meriting hath for reward ſome higher degree of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall glory; which degree ſhould not haue bin purchaſed without that meritorious worke had bin done: ſo that if there be two men, who before were of equall merits, &amp; the one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould but giue a cup of cold water more for Chriſts ſake, then the other ſhould giue, this man for this ſo ſmall a good work, ſhould haue a higher degree of glory then the other, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently he ſhould ſee God for all eternity more perfectly, and be for euer more happy then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So that if we did truly loue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:42934:40"/>
God or our ſelues, we ſhould thinke all ſufferings whatſoeuer, euen thoſe of Purgatory, to be a ſmall price for the leaſt degree of glory, for indeed the leaſt is a good ſo great, that the ſuffering of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo long a Purgatory for pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing it, would not be ſo much as ſuffering a flea-bite to purchaſe the Empire of the whole world. It would make a man bleſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſee, how ſtarke mad men are in neglecting ſuch a good.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To our purpoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I ſay, that by applying our actions to the ſoules in Purgatory we do merit more, then if we had not applyed them to this end; and not onely more, but very much more: and therefore though we did ſuſtayne other many, and great inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, yet they were all to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as nothing in compariſon of theſe ineſtimable treaſures of merit, which by this deuotion we purchaſe. The cauſes which make
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:42934:41"/>
this act of ſo high merit, may be many, for as we haue ſhewed in the ſixt chapter, this deuotion may be a worke of moſt ſingular Charity, moſt admirable Gratitude, moſt rare Contrition, moſt tender loue towards our Lord &amp; Sauiour. But that which in a particular manner doth rayſe the worth of this actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is the moſt ardent charity, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mercy towards our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, which here is ſo reſplenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that it doth containe, and ſurpaſſe all and euery one of thoſe works of mercy which our Sauiour eſteems ſo dearly, that vnto them by name he ſhall giue the eternall poſſeſſion of heauen, when he ſhall come to iudge. For he ſhall ſay vnto thoſe who ſtand at the right and: <hi>Come yee bleſsed of my Father and poſſeſſe the kingdome prepared for you from the making of the world, for J was hungry and you gaue me to eate, I was thirſty and you gaue me to drinke, a pilgrime and you entertained me, naked &amp; you
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:42934:41"/>
cloathed me, ſick and you did viſit me, impriſoned and you came vnto me. Matth.</hi> 25. This act, I ſay, both conteyneth, &amp; ſurpaſſeth all thoſe works put togeather. For who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieueth a ſoule in Purgatory, though he giueth not a peece of bread to the hungry, yet he giueth the food of life &amp; bread of Angels to one, who was tormented worſe then death with the hunger of it. He giueth not a cup of cold water to the thirſty, but he giueth the fountaine of liuing water, which runneth into life euerlaſting, vnto him, whoſe thirſt of it was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable, that no paine in the world can be compared to it. He doth not lodge a poore harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les pilgrime in a barne for a night, but for the whole long day of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, he lodgeth in the heauenly manſions, a poore ſoule, which wandred from this her home euer ſince her creation. He giueth not a few caſt-of rags to cloath the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:42934:42"/>
but he giueth the marriage garment vnto him, who for want of it was caſt for a time into out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward darknes. He doth not giue a comfortable viſit vnto one who lyeth ſicke of a burning feauer; but him, who burneth with Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory flames, he carrieth to viſit for euer God, and his Angels. In fine, he doth not goe to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned to afford them ſome ſmal aſſiſtance, but he bringeth one out of the fiery dungeon of Purgatory into the liberty of the children of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Another cauſe there is, which doth wonderfully exagerate the worth of all theſe things, which followeth in the aboue cited Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. For when the Bleſſed ſhall ſay: Lord when haue we ſeene thee hungry, &amp; fed thee? our Lord ſhall anſwere them: <hi>Verily I ſay vnto you, as long as you haue done any of theſe things to one of theſe my least brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you haue done them vnto me.</hi> O what
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:42934:42"/>
reward ſhall be haue of ſo liberall a maieſty, who hath done ſo grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a ſeruice, as the very freeing of Chriſt himſelfe from Purgatory (if ſo he could be liable vnto it) would be.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The cauſe which may make the merit of this act to amount to an inconceptible greatnes, is this, that thoſe who are truly deuoted to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt theſe ſoules, receiue daily ſuch copious ſhowers of diuine graces, that, if they be not very backward in correſponding vnto them, they muſt needs go on daily increaſing the treaſures of their merits? For though many doubt, whether the ſoules whilſt they remaine in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory do pray for him by name who doth pray for them (becauſe they not ſeeing God, cannot know who they are who pray for them) yet there ſeemes to be all reaſon that they ſhould make in a generall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner inceſſant prayer to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God to bleſſe all thoſe, who
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:42934:43"/>
ſhall pray for them; for this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is both pious and probable, as <hi>Snares</hi> ſaith, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de orat. c.</hi> 2. And <hi>Denis</hi> the Carthuſian recounteth, how that in a diuine reuelation, theſe words by a ſeruant of God were heard to be vttered with the common voyce of the ſoules in Purgatory: <hi>O Lord God grant, out of thy incomprehenſible power, a hundred fold reward to all thoſe in the world who with their prayers do help vs, and lift vs vp towards the light of thy dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. (de indic. anim. circa finem.)</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, no man can doubt, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come to heauen, they will both day &amp; night, as efficaciouſly as they can recommend vnto Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God the neceſſityes of all thoſe, who were ſo charitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, as to obtaine their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery out of their horrible torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and to purchaſe for them the light of God, whome to ſee one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſooner, they know now what a good it is.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:42934:43"/>6. What gratefull hart then, can euer forget ſuch a benefactour, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when without any labour at all, yea with greateſt pleaſure &amp; content, he can abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dantly requite his charity. Ingratitude is a vice, &amp; hath no place in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. More grat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full therfore queſtionles will theſe ſoules be, moſt gratfull will be all their friends, acquaintance, &amp; kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, their Angel-guardians, and Patrons, yea all the whole Court of heauen; ſeeing that there is that perfect charity amongſt the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that euery one of them is no leſſe glad of his neighbours good, then he is of his owne: &amp; this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is incomparably more gratfull vnto them, in regard that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the diuine Maieſty is much increaſed, and our Bleſſed Sauiour ſo ſingularly pleaſed by it, that it is as acceptable vnto him, as if he himſelfe in perſon had bin the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deliuered from the paines of Purgatory, and brought to a more
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:42934:44"/>
ſpeedy fruition of eternall beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. O my deare brother, depriue not theſe poore ſoules, of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, thy ſelfe of theſe merits, the whole Court of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this ioy, Chriſt of this comfort, God of this honour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> That our actions offered vp for the ſoules in Purgatory, are not leſſe, but more impetratory of other fauours.</head>
               <p n="1">1. FIRST I muſt intreat my Reader to call to mind that, which in the laſt Chapter but one hath bin ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the impetratory vertue of our actions, which being applyed to the ſoules in Purgatory accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſatisfactory vertue only, reteyne notwithſtanding the ſelfe ſame vertue to impetrate, which they ſhould haue had, thogh
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:42934:44"/>
they had not bin thus applyed for as I ſatisfy for my ſins by that very Prayer, by which I beg my daily bread, and the obtaining of this petition, is nothing hindered by this ſatisfaction; ſo the worke which ſatisfieth for the ſins of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, doth not become leſſe apt to mooue the Goodnes of God to the graunt of any fauour, for obteyning of which, this worke may alſo be offered. Wherefore they are in an errour, who thinke that they muſt caſt all other deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions aſide, and neither pray for themſelues, nor for their frends, nor for their owne priuat, or the publike neceſſityes, if they follow our aduice in praying, faſting, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing almes, &amp; offering vp all their other good works for the ſoules in Purgatory; whereas all theſe things may be performed without the leaſt hinderance to the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of any thing they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requeſt: for theſe works only, as they are
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:42934:45"/>
ſatisfactory, may be applyed for the reliefe of theſe ſoules, and as they are impetratory, they may be offered vp for the obteyning of what we pleaſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. True it is, that ſometyms the very thing, which we do deſire, &amp; petition in our prayers, is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of the ſoules in Purgatory, &amp; we do actually craue, intreat, and beg for this; and vnto this our ſo earneſt requeſt we do ioyne other works of faſting, almeſdeeds &amp;c. to moue the mercy of God to heare graciouſly this our petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; then we need not wonder if our prayers, as they are impetratory, do not impetrate for vs other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, for we neuer did demand them: ſo when I pray for the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alth of my Father, this prayer of mine doth not impetrate the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alth of my mother: and euen as, when I pray for both the health of my Father and of my Mother, this prayer of mine is not ſo efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:42934:45"/>
to obtaine the health of my Father, as it would haue bin, if it had bin made for that end onely and no other: ſo I pray for other things, and alſo for the ſoules in Purgatory, this prayer of mine is not perhaps ſo efficacious to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thoſe other things, as it would haue bin, if it had bin made for thoſe only, and for nothing els. I did ſay (perhaps) for there be many reaſons (as we ſhall ſee preſently) for which Prayer, thus made, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth very efficacious for the obtaining thoſe other requeſtes, which I deſire to haue granted, &amp; which perhaps may further the grant of them, far more then pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them alone would do.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But for the preſent, let vs ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that ſuch a prayer is leſſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall for obtaining of other things; yet this ought not to make men more backward to pray for the ſoules in Purgatory; for ſhall I neuer pray for my Mother, becauſe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:42934:46"/>
by the ſame prayer I obtaine ſome what leſſe for my Father, then I ſhould haue done, if I had prayed for him only? In the choice of thes intentions, for which we pray, we muſt regard many things, as the greater glory of God, the neceſſity of our Neighbour, our owne ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall aduancement, the common good of the Church, and the like. Now perhaps all things well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, there will ſcarce be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one thinge, which ought ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly to be commended to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions as praying for the dead, in the which, among other thinges, there is alſo this to be noted, that as <hi>S. Thomas</hi> ſaith, <hi>in ſuppl.</hi> 3. <hi>p. q.</hi> 21. <hi>a.</hi> 5. <hi>God doth rather accept of prayers for the dead then for the liuing becauſe they not being able, as the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing are, to help themſelues, do more stand in need of the help of others.</hi> To the which we may ad a worthy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of <hi>S. Denis,</hi> that famous diſciple of <hi>S. Paul (de Eccl. Hier. c.</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:42934:46"/>
7. <hi>p.</hi> 5.) to wit, that when we pray for the liuing, our prayer many ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, as it is impetratory, obtaineth nothing at all, becauſe the thing we pray for is not conuenient to be granted, or becauſe (to vſe his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) the ſins of thoſe we pray for, do hinder this effect: as the ſins of <hi>Saul</hi> did hinder that the prayers of <hi>Samuel</hi> could not be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard in his behalf, 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 15.16. This in praying for the dead doth neuer take place, for thoſe who are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted in Gods grace, as <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine, in Enchir. c.</hi> 100. teacheth, <hi>deſerued whilst they liued, that theſe helps of prayers might profit them after their death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Let vs come now to the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for which (as I began to infinuate) our prayers are far more impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory when we remember the dead in them, then when we omit this charitable remembrance. The firſt reaſon is, becauſe this praying for the dead, is an act of mercy ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:42934:47"/>
that it doth in a ſuper-emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent manner containe and ſurpaſſe all the corporall deeds of mercy put together, as hath bin demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated. Now, there is no more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious meanes to ſtir vp the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and liberality of God towards vs, then the exerciſe of works of mercy and liberality: For as our Sauiour ſaith <hi>Math.</hi> 6. <hi>Bleſſed be the mercifull, becauſe they shall obtaine mercy.</hi> And againe, <hi>Marc.</hi> 4. <hi>In what meaſure you shall meaſure vnto others, it shall be meaſured back to goe againe, (&amp; adijcietur vobis) and meaſured back with great increaſe.</hi> Will you know with how great? <hi>S. Luke</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you: <hi>A good meaſure, a heaped meaſure, a meaſure preſſed downe, &amp; running ouer they shall giue into your boſome. Luc.</hi> 6. With what words could the largneſſe of this meaſure haue bin more fully ſet forth? And indeed of ſo good a God we could expect no other: far be it from him that our liberality ſhould rather
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:42934:47"/>
ſhut, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> open his hands. His deeds will euer prooue his ſaying true: <hi>Giue, &amp; it shall be giuen vnto you,</hi> in the meaſure declared vnto you, in this very place.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And we may be the more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of this particuler act, becauſe our Sauiour taketh it as done vnto himſelfe; and therefore doubtles as thoſe ſoules, which we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, cannot but be moſt ready to further any iuſt petition, which we ſhall make ſo our deare Lord, who counteth himſelfe to be the perſon releaſed, will neuer be wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the furtherance of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we ſhall piouſly deſire. Now, to haue his good word ſo ſure on our ſide, muſt needs be of greater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence for obtaining any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable fauour, then any thing we can deuiſe. And as far as my ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity can reach, I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner we may more efficaciouſly compaſſe the grant of al our moſt important requeſts,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:42934:48"/>
then by thus obliging (as I may ſay) Chriſt our Lord to ſpeake in our behalfe with that earneſtnes, which we may imagin thoſe ſoules to vſe whom we haue relieued.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The R. F. <hi>Alexis de Salo</hi> writeth thus of himſelfe, <hi>Part. 1.</hi> §. 2. <hi>One of my particuler denotions is, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I deſire to obtaine any fauour for my ſelfe, or any other, to ſay ſome few prayers for the dead; and J aſſure you, J haue experienced in my ſelfe &amp; others, strange effects.</hi> Many haue found and ſtill do find wonderfull fauours in their iourneys by offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the labour of that dayes tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, or doing ſome other good work for the ſoules in Purgatory, ſo that in ſome places this is very commonly practiſed; and many ſuch like deuotions are of more admirable effect then men will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily belieue.</p>
               <p n="7">7. A further reaſon why our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, when we remember the ſoules of Purgatory in them, do become
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:42934:48"/>
of far greater efficacy to obtaine our requeſts, is this: Becauſe (as hath bin inſinuated) this prayer, though of it ſelfe it hath not this greater efficacy, yet what it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of it ſelfe, it procureth to be far more effectually performed by the help of thoſe voices, which it winneth, amonge which the firſt place is to be giuen to the <hi>Word</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate, whoſe words cannot but be heard: <hi>I did know, that thou dost alwayes heare me,</hi> ſaith this our Lord <hi>Joan.</hi> 9. The voices alſo of Heauens whole Court cannot but ioyne with the <hi>Word,</hi> both becauſe their affections are vnited with an inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable true-louers-knot, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is not one in heauen, who thinketh not himſelfe to haue particuler intereſt in the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of this cauſe; for all that Bleſſed manſion loue the ſoule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they loue their owne ſoules, <hi>and therfore</hi> (as a graue Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſaith) <hi>they all reioyce at the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:42934:49"/>
of euery one of their Bretheren, as much as at their owne. (Hugo l.</hi> 4. <hi>de anim. c.</hi> 15.) and conſequently all and euery one of them will be in a manner as forward to aſſiſt vs, as thoſe ſoules will be, who were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed by our prayers. And who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expreſſe how ready theſe ſoules releaſed, or releiued by vs, are to help vs in all occurences? Tell me now, what meanes can you inuent more efficacious to make, in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſure whatſoeuer you requeſt?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> That by offering our Actions for the Soules in Purgatory, we do not leſſe, but more ſatisfy for our owne Sinnes.</head>
               <p n="1">1. NOw we come to that point, which onely hath difficulty in this matter; for it may ſeeme clear that when we giue away to others the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:42934:49"/>
fruits of our owne ſatisfaction, we cannot enioy theſe fruits our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, no more then we can pay our debts with the ſame mony which we pay for the debts of our fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. This difficulty is very ſolidly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by ſaying that, which is moſt true, to wit, that to pray for, and aſſiſt the ſoules in Purgatory is an act ſo highly meritorious of grace and glory, an act ſo impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of ſuch things as may be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally beneficial to our owne ſoules that the loſſe of the fruit of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions is nothing to be valued in regard of the gaine, which we purchaſe, as may appeare by what hath bin ſaid before <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>nu.</hi> 2. A ſecond, and ſufficient anſwere might be, that this loſſe may fully be repayred by the gayning of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces for our ſelues. So though I cannot pay my owne debts with the ſame mony which I pay out for the debts of my friends, yet I may by fauour, procure a releaſment of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:42934:50"/>
my owne debts, and ſo be as free from them, as if I had payd them with that mony, which I liberally layd out to diſcharge my frends debt. That ſuch fauours or Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences may be obtayned, we will proue at large <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But theſe two Anſwers being for the preſent let paſſe, I intend to make good the title of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to ſhew that this deuotion is a rare kind of ſatisfaction. For vnderſtanding of which it is much to be noted, that when we do any good worke for the ſoules in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, for example when we faſt or pray, or giue almes for them, we haue ſuch a kind of act, as this is, <hi>J do offer this Faſt, this Prayer, this Almes, for ſuch a ſoule, or ſoules in Purgatory.</hi> The thing therefore which we giue away, is only ſuch a faſt, prayer, or almes, and of the fruit of this worke as it is ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, we wholy depriue our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, &amp; conſequently as it is ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:42934:50"/>
it maketh no ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our ſinnes, but only for their ſins for whom we did offer it: yet that act, by which I, offering this Faſt for another, depriue my ſelfe of the fruit therof, redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth wholy to my profit: neyther doth any part of it benefit any one, but my ſelfe. Now I affirme that with this act, by which with ſo great charity to God &amp; my neighbour, I giue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way this faſt, this almes, this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, I do both ſatisfy for my ſinnes, and ſatisfy in no meane manner, but in a manner far more excellent then is ordinarily conceaued.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For firſt this is an act moſt meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, &amp; conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly moſt ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory. For as the learned <hi>Vaſquez</hi> teacheth 2. <hi>p. q.</hi> 94. <hi>dub.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 3. Euery good worke for the ſelf ſame cauſe for which it doth deſerue to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded in heauen, deſerueth alſo freedom from ſuch impediments as may hinder the enioying of this reward, ſuch an impediment as the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:42934:51"/>
being in Purgatory would be. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouer, the more that we by our good deeds do endeare our ſelues to the diuine Maieſty, the more we do recompence any former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure done vnto him. Gratefull ſeruices cannot but aboliſh old offences. Hence alſo Deuines of prime note do auerre, that all good acts are in the ſelfe ſame degree ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory, in which they are meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious. So ſaith <hi>Victoria, Soto, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſma &amp;c.</hi> Now, we haue demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated that this act is in a very high degree meritorious, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by conſequence it muſt be in a very high degree ſatisfactory.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But let vs conſider a little more this act by it ſelfe: Firſt it cannot but be hard and laborious to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted nature to be willing to faſt for another, pray for another, giue almes for another: and if this be not very difficult, why do you hold back ſo much, ſeing it may be ſo beneficiall vnto you: If you
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:42934:51"/>
find no difficulty, becauſe your Charity towards your neighbour is ſuch, that with ioy you can do all theſe things for his ſake; this pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpoſition of yours, doth not leſſen, but increaſe the ſatisfactory vertue of this act. For as excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly <hi>S. Thomas, in ſuppl. q.</hi> 15. <hi>a. 1. The leſſening of the payne which proceeds from the readines of the will cauſed by Charity, doth not diminish, but incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſe the efficacy of our ſatisfaction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Againe, this is an act of rare Charity towards God, whoſe glory we aduance by thus procuring the increaſe of his honour done to him in heauen by the ſoules we releaſe, and towards our Neighbour, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we procure the greateſt good that may be. Now (as <hi>Konincke</hi> ſaith, <hi>de Sacram. diſp.</hi> 10. <hi>de ſatisf. dub.</hi> 4.) <hi>Not a few, but all Deuines do teach, that by an act of charity produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with neuer ſo much eaſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, a man may ſatisfy for all the paines he hath deſerued.</hi> The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:42934:52"/>
telleth vs as much: <hi>Many ſinnes are forgiuen her, becauſe she hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued much. Luc.</hi> 7. <hi>Aboue all things hauing continuall mutuall charity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your ſelues, becauſe charity doth couer the multitude of ſinnes.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. And if this be not inough, <hi>Charity doth couer all our ſinnes. Prou.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Laſtly this act is one of the chiefeſt deeds of mercy, ſurpaſſing all the works of corporall mercy put togeather, and therefore que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe it is an act moſt highly ſatisfactory: for if of all corporall Almes it be written, that they <hi>free from ſinne and death, and do not ſuffer the ſoule to go into darknes, Tob.</hi> 4. That they <hi>reſist ſin as water doth the burning fire. Eccl.</hi> 3. That if you <hi>giue almes all shalbe clean vnto you. Luc.</hi> 11. What ſhall we thinke of this ſpirituall almes, by which heauen is giuen, and purgatory paines for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen to a poore ſoule, made of a moſt pittifull priſoner, a moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Saint. What a worke of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:42934:52"/>
is this? Of the works of mercy in generall <hi>S. Thomas</hi> ſayth. 2.2. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>a.</hi> 2. <hi>The works of ſpirituall mercy are ſo much more excellent then the works of corporall mercy, by how much the ſoule is more noble then the body.</hi> By this it appeareth that all thoſe who exerciſe theſe works of charity &amp; ſpirituall mercy frequently (as all do who do much for the ſoules in Purgatory) are ſo far from depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing themſelues of all ſatisfaction, that as often as they giue their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory works away, they heap vp great treaſures of ſatisfaction: ſo that heere that which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayth in the Prouerbs, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly verifyed: <hi>Some men diuide to others their owne riches, and become the richer therby. Prou.</hi> 24.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:42934:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> That by offering our Actions for the Soules in Purgatory, we haue great hope of eſcaping eyther all, or a good part of Purgatory.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THE proofe of this title may be in part drawne out of the precedent chapters, for this act being ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent if we regard merit, and ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall if we regard impetration, may with good grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be thought partly to deſerue as it is merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, partly to obtaine by way of fauour as it is impetratory, that our mercifull Lord ſhould deale more mildely, then the ordinary courſe of iuſtice exacts, with all thoſe who haue both made a moſt noble kind of ſatisfaction for their owne ſinnes, and haue with a moſt heroicall charity, done many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to ſatisfy for the ſinnes
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:42934:53"/>
of others: neyther be there wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting many conuenient reaſons to perſwade vs to haue this honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conceit of the diuine goodnes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The holy Scripture it ſelfe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues vs good ground to build this opinion. <hi>Charity doth couer the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſinnes.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. And yet more clearly: <hi>Charity doth couer all our ſinnes. Prou.</hi> 10. And what Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity more eminent then this: <hi>Almes free from ſinne, and from death, and permit not the ſoule to go into darknes? Tob.</hi> 4. <hi>Giue almes, and all shall be clean vnto you. Luc.</hi> 11. Now if theſe prerogatiues be to be granted to almes deeds, when they are plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful (which I add becauſe S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome ſayth, <hi>Non dare, ſed copioſè dare, eleemoſyna est: Not to giue, but to giue plentifully, is an almeeſdeed)</hi> if I ſay almeſdeeds be thus priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, being a meere worke of mercy corporall; what ſhall we thinke of this almes ſo inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſurpaſſing all corporall works
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:42934:54"/>
of mercy, for it relieueth a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miſery then any corporall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity can be, and it beſtoweth a gift no leſſe then the poſſeſſion of God himſelfe? Shall ſuch an almes permit the giuer of it to go into darknes? Now this almes alſo will make all cleare: for, <hi>He who giueth to the poore shall not want. Prou.</hi> 27. He ſhall not ſuſtaine this neceſſity the moſt grieuous a poore ſoule can be in, becauſe as holy <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. <hi>Bleſſed is he who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth concerning the poore and needy, in the euill day our Lord will deliuer him.</hi> He ſhall be deliuered in that day which to others is ſo euill.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And indeed how can we thinke otherwiſe, for be not theſe our Sauiours words: As long as you haue done theſe things vnto any one of my Bretheren, you haue done them vnto me? Now if our Sauiour taketh the deliuery of the Soules of his bretheren as grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:42934:54"/>
as if his owne ſoule had bin freed from Purgatory; what ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of likelyhood is there, that he will not procure the deliuery of him whom he acknowledgeth to haue bin his owne deliuerer? who of vs can haue the heart (and our harts are hard inough) yet who of vs can haue the hart, to let him lye roſting in Purgatory flames, who hath freed vs from this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, eſpecially if we could effect his releaſment as eaſily as our Sauiour can worke ours, euen without breach of the very rigor of iuſtice, to wit, by offering in our behalfe his ſuperabundant ſatisfactions for the ſupply of ſuch ſatisfaction as we ſtand in need of, that is, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow for his own ſake a Plenary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence vpon vs, which though it be a fauour extraordinary, yet the motiue to grant it beareth propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with ſuch a grant; and to him who hath ſhewed ſo extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry charity, liberality, and mercy,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:42934:55"/>
it ought not to ſeeme ſtrange, if extraordinary charity, liberality, &amp; mercy be ſhewed by him whoſe bowels are made all of Charity, bounty, and compaſſion: for if in puniſhing God obſerueth this rule: <hi>By what things a man ſinneth by the ſame alſo he is tormented. Sap.</hi> 11. <hi>As he hath done, ſo it shall be done vnto him. He shall reſtore ſoule for ſoule, eye for eye. Leuit.</hi> 29. May we not iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly thinke, that in matter of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour he doth ſhew greateſt mercy to him, who hath ſhewed greateſt mercy to others? what other ſenſe haue thoſe words, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Bleſſed be the mercifull, for they shall obtaine mercy?</hi> Wherfore, <hi>As he hath done, it shall be done vnto him.</hi> As he hath offered his ſatisfactions for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſment of the Soules of Chriſts bretheren, ſo Chriſt will offer vp his ſuperabundant ſatisfaction for the releaſment of his Soule, <hi>Soule for Soule shall be repayed to him,</hi> ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom for ranſom. As he hath freed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:42934:55"/>
others ſo he ſhal be freed himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We muſt not heere ouerſlip in a curſory manner that euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t text of Scripture, which doth almoſt demonſtrate that which we haue ſaid, <hi>Giue and it shalbe giuen vnto you:</hi> but marke well in what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>A good meaſure, a heaped mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, a meaſure preſſed downe, and running ouer, they shall giue into your boſome. Luc.</hi> 6. The thing which we did giue, was the fruits of our ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for ſupply of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s want, by which guift he was releaſed. Wherfore that our Lord may returne vs equall meaſure, as great wants of ours muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by the fruits of his ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſatisfactions, but that this meaſure be <hi>a heaped vp, a preſſed downe, and running ouer meaſure,</hi> we may expect to be in that ouer libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall manner, made partakers of Chriſts ſatisfactions, that by them our debts being to the laſt farthing wholy diſcharged, we may paſſe
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:42934:56"/>
without impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the reward of our charity.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To all theſe ſo well grounded reaſons we will add for a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the certaine aſſiſtance which infallibly in this our neceſſity will be affoarded vs, by all thoſe whom we haue either releaſed or relieued, and not only all theſe happy ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, but alſo all, and euery one of their bleſſed kindred, Angel-guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, Patrons &amp;c. will fauour vs in our death, to requite the fauour by which we obliged them in our life: ſo that many of the Saints by their glorious interceſſions, &amp; ſome by offering vp for vs their ſuperabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſatisfactions, will ſo preuayle with the mercy of God, that we need not much feare, all helps be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put togeather, to be long left forlorn in the flames of Purgatory.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And leaſt perhaps this feare might haue ſome little place left in any mans hart, it hath pleaſed the diuine goodnes by word of mouth
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:42934:56"/>
to confirme all we haue ſaid. S. <hi>Gertrude</hi> was one of the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Saints for vertue, and one of the moſt wonderfull Saints for the miraculous fauours which dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were done vnto her, that the Church hath had. This bleſſed Saint (as <hi>Denis</hi> the Carthuſian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth) did with an admirable affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, giue all, and euery of her actions wholy vnto the ſoules in Purgatory, not reſeruing for her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the leaſt fruit of her ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming therfore to dy ſhe began not a litle to be afflicted in mind for feare, leaſt that hauing many ſinnes to ſatisfy for, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing left herſelf deſtitute of all her ſatisfactory workes, ſhe might be lyable to grieuous puniſhments. But Chriſt himſelfe did vouchſafe to comfort her with theſe words: <hi>That thou mayst vnderstand how gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefull that charity of thine hath bin vnto me, which thou didst shew to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſoules, I do euen now forgiue
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:42934:57"/>
thee all thoſe paines which thou shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt haue ſuffered. And J who for one haue promiſed a hundredfold, will now shew my liberality, and I will heap vp glory vpon thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. This comfort may they expect who haue ſhewed the like mercy towards the ſoules of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: but thoſe who haue ſlighted this deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſuperſtitious, or fit only for old wiues, may iuſtly feare to haue thoſe dreadfull words ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto them: <hi>Justice without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to him, who hath not done mercy. Iac.</hi> 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> That it is not against charity to our ſelues to offer our Actions for the ſoules in Purgatory but it is rather against it, not to offer them.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THE common and the only obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which any Catholike can
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:42934:57"/>
make againſt this liberality to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſoules in Purgatory is this: That though our prayers, or other good works, offered vp to God for the ſoules in Purgatory, be equally, or rather more, both meritorious and impetratory then otherwiſe they wold haue bin; yet it cannot be denyed, but that they do not ſatisfy for our owne ſinnes: which ſeing that they be many and great, the paines due vnto them wilbe exceſſiue; and therfore if our Charity were well ordered, we would not ſo forget our ſelues, as to leaue our ſelues in this manner depriued of thoſe ſatisfactions, for want of which we ſhalbe lyable to theſe torments which be ſo very terrible. This obiection I haue dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to this place, becauſe now the anſwers vnto it, out of that which hath bin ſayd, will be moſt cleare.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I anſwer then firſt, that though we did become lyable to theſe &amp;
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:42934:58"/>
greater paines, yet they were not ſo much to be eſteemed as a flea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byte for gaining of a kingdom, if by this our Charity towards the ſoules, we might increaſe (as we do moſt highly increaſe) the crowne of our eternall glory. See <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. I anſwere ſecondly, that by the gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Indulgences we may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent this pretended incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as we ſhall proue at large in the 14. Chapter.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, I giue this direct and cleare anſwer, that though by the works we do for the ſoules, we do ſatisfy only for their, and not at all for our owne ſinnes; yet by that rare act of Charity, by which we giue theſe works away vnto them, we do ſatisfy in a moſt high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as hath bin proued in the 10. Chapter; yea in a degree ſo high, that by this ſatisfaction (&amp; other helps, as we did demonſtrate in the laſt Chapter) we haue great hope of eſcaping either all, or greateſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:42934:58"/>
part of Purgatory.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To conclude this Chapter, in a word it is nothing againſt well-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Charity towards our ſelues, to help theſe ſoules as much as we can; but it needs muſt be againſt perfection of this Charity, not to aſſiſt them to our full power; for that we looſe the merit of ſo rare a charity, and the loſſe of this merit is a loſſe of the perfecter ſight of God for euer. If we loue either God or our ſelues, this will moue vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> By what meanes we may help the ſoules in Purgatory.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IF God hath done vs the fauor to ſoften our harts, we ſhall not now deſire any new motiues, but rather ſeeke by what meanes we may chiefly relieue theſe poore ſoules. For thoſe, who are thus diſpoſed, we
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:42934:59"/>
will declare what is to be done in this matter.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That which in the firſt place ought to be recommended is, that if they will indeed benefit either their owne ſoules, or ſatisfy for the ſouls of their neighbours, they muſt put themſelues in the ſtate of grace: for a dead member can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther help the body, of which it is a member, nor any body els. And S. Paul ſayth, <hi>1. Cor. 13. Although I should distribute al my goods, although I should deliuer vp my body to burne, yet if I should not haue charity, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing.</hi> This ſuppoſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ordinary meanes of relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the dead be theſe: Prayer, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, &amp; almesdeeds. As for prayer for the dead, it is a thing inſtituted by the Apoſtles themſelues, as we proued in the firſt Chapter; and ſo eſteemed by the holy Church, that at the end of euery houre of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine office, ſhe teacheth vs to pray, that the ſoules of the faythful may
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:42934:59"/>
reſt in peace; for ſhe wold not haue vs pray at any houre, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring theſe afflicted ſoules in our Prayers. It would make one wonder to ſee, with what affection <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> in the two laſt Chapters of his ninth booke of his Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, doth pray for the ſoule of his dead Mother: &amp; not content with his owne prayers, he doth earneſtly craue and beg the prayers of all, in theſe fiery wordes. <hi>Inſpire, O Lord, inſpire into thy ſeruants, that as many as shall read theſe things, may be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at thy Altar, of Monica thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, that that which she dïd last of all request of me, may be the more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully performed by the prayers of many.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. But among all kind of prayers there is none comparable to the oblation of the dreadfull Sacrifice of the Maſſe, for in this Sacrifice the ſelf-ſame Chriſt is offered in an vnbloudy manner vpon the altar, who was offered in a bloudy man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner vpon the croſſe. So ſayth <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:42934:60"/>
in Hebr. 10. We offer alwayes one and the ſame Sacrifice, and not one Lambe to morrow, and another to day, but alwayes the ſame, one Chriſt is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, heere fully, and there fully.</hi> And againe, <hi>l. 1. in Luc. c. 1. When we ſacrifice, Christ is preſent, Christ is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed.</hi> For as <hi>S. Austin</hi> ſayth <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>de Trin. c.</hi> 14. <hi>The flesh of our Sacrifice is made the body of our Priest.</hi> Wherfore that moſt ancient, and glorious Martyr <hi>S. Hippolitus</hi> in his Oration <hi>de Conſummatione mundi,</hi> bringeth in our Sauiour thus ſpeaking vnto our Prieſts: <hi>Come you who dayly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice my body, and my bloud.</hi> And Chriſt ſayth this to all Prieſts; for as excellently <hi>S. Chryſostome hom. 2. ïn 2. ad Tim. The ſacred oblation what Priest ſoeuer offers it, is stil the ſame: for men do not ſacrifice this victime but Chriſt himſelf.</hi> Wherfore the victime which in this Sacrifice is offered being true Chriſt, &amp; the ſelfe ſame Chriſt being chief Prieſt, which by his miniſters and ſubſtitutes doth
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:42934:60"/>
ſanctify and offer this victime, can any one wonder, if all we Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, together with <hi>S. Cyril of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem (Cath. mystag.</hi> 5.) <hi>Do belieue that the obſecration of that holy and dreadfull Sacrifice, which is placed on the altar, is the greatest help for the ſoules, for which it is offered.</hi> See this place at large, for nothing can be ſpoken more Catholikly.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Sacrifices of the old Law were eſteemed by the chiefe &amp; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true belieuers of thoſe tymes to haue ſuch vertue to relieue the dead, that when ſouldiers were ſlaine in battaile, they made a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of no leſſe then <hi>twelue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand drachmes of ſiluer, and ſent this money to Hieruſalem, that ſacrifice might be offered for the ſins of the dead.</hi> 2. <hi>Machab.</hi> 12. What eſteeme then ought we to haue of our Sacrifice? <hi>S. Auſtin l. 9. Confeſſ. c. 3.</hi> deſeruedly prayſed his dead Mother in theſe words; <hi>She did not thinke how to haue her body ſumptuouſly buried, or embal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:42934:61"/>
but she deſired only that her me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory might be made at Gods Altar, at which she neuer omitted any one day of her life to be preſent, knowing that from thence is diſpenſed the holy hoast or Sacrifice, wherby is blotted out the guilt of the world.</hi> And this which ſhe requeſted was fulfilled, <hi>when the Sacrifice of our price was offered for her,</hi> as <hi>S. Austin cap.</hi> 12. of the ſame Booke, ſayth it was.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This piety which ſo flouriſhed in the primitiue Church, ceaſeth not in the prime parts of the world to flouriſh in theſe our dayes. No leſſe then one thouſand &amp; ſeauen hundred Maſſes, vpon one and the ſelfe ſame day, were in <hi>Madrid</hi> ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated at the funerals of <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> wife to Philip the third, King of <hi>Spaine:</hi> and beſides a thouſand Maſſes which this Queene by her will gaue order to haue ſaid for her Soule, the King of his liberality cauſed twenty thouſand more to be ſaid for her. <hi>Gaſman. in vita
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:42934:61"/>
Margar. Austriac. p.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. It is not very many yeares ſince the death of the Archduke <hi>Albertus</hi> Prince of the Low-Countryes, whoſe moſt pious wife <hi>Iſabell</hi> did procure for the reliefe of his ſoule forty thouſand Maſſes, and for thirty dayes togeather ſhe herſelfe did heare 10. Maſſes daily for this her pious Lord and husband. <hi>P.F. Iac. Curuoiſier in Manſolaeo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. As for faſting moſt remarkable is that which we read in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: That after the death of <hi>Saul</hi> &amp; his ſonnes, <hi>the men of Iabes Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laad did take his dead body, and the dead bodyes of his ſonnes, and buried them in the wood of Jabes, and fasted ſeauen dayes.</hi> 1. <hi>Reg. c. vlt.</hi> Vnder the name of faſts all other mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and auſterityes are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, as diſciplines, hayre-cloath, lying on the ground &amp;c. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome mens ſilken eares can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure ſo hard language, as the naming of theſe things; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:42934:62"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:42934:62"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:42934:63"/>
vnder pretence of health will plead inhability to performe ſuch works, I will adde ſome few acts of mortification, which no man, or woman can be too weake to exerciſe. For example, to debarre themſelues of ſome leſſe neceſſary recreations, to abſtaine from ſome ſweet morſels, for ſome ſmal ſpace to keep ſilence, not to ſee, not to heare ſuch, and ſuch curioſities. But one act of Vertue there is, which the weakeſt creature in the world may practiſe, and it is an act of ſo high worth, that the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt man in the world can ſcarce pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice a better. It is this: for Chriſts ſake to forgiue all thoſe, from your very hart, who haue done any iniury, or iniuries vnto you. This is not my doctrine, but the doctrine of <hi>S. Auſtin Serm.</hi> 41. <hi>de Sanctis,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>Thoſe who deſire to be deliuered from this tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall purging fire, let them by continual prayers, and frequent faſtings, &amp; large
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:42934:63"/>
almes, and eſpecially by forgiuing them who haue offended against them, redeeme their ordinary dayly ſins.</hi> This act which <hi>S. Austin</hi> doth ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, aboue all other, commend, hath a better recommendation in the word of God, which doth in plaine termes promiſe to this act a plenary Indulgence, a Iubily, a full Remiſſion of all ſins in this large forme of Grant: <hi>Forgiue, and it shall be forgiuen vnto you. Luc. 6.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: <hi>For if you forgiue vnto men their offences, your heauenly Father alſo will forgiue your ſins vnto you. Matth.</hi> 6. This pardon you may gaine for the ſoules in Purgatory. Heare then a memorable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="8">8 The only ſonne of an honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Widdow was murdered by a wicked fellow, who being for this his murder in danger of being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the Officers, had hid himſelfe: but the officers, and the widdow had intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce where
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:42934:64"/>
he lay. The Officers went to the place to take him, but the pious widdow did, for Gods ſake, ſo tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pardon this greateſt miſchiefe which could haue byn done her, that ſhe did not onely certify the murderer of his danger, to the end he might fly away in tyme, but for this end did ſhe furniſh him alſo with money, and gaue him the horſe of her dead ſonne, that he might eſcape the better. After this ſhe retired herſelfe to pray for her Sonnes ſoule, when behold her ſonne all in glory appeared vnto her, and told her that for ſo great Charity towards his murderer, God had already freed him from the fire of Purgatory, which for many yeares he ſhould haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Oroſius fer.</hi> 6. <hi>post Cineres.</hi> Thus much for this point. We may alſo much relieue the ſoules in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory by ſuffering for them ſuch croſſes as it ſhall pleaſe God to lay vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: as ſicknes, loſſe of goods, of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:42934:64"/>
friends, trouble of the mind, and all kind of afflictions, which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſatisfactory, if we accept them willingly, or beare them pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently.</p>
               <p n="6">6. A third kind of ſatisfaction moſt auailable to the ſoules in Purgatory, is to exerciſe Almes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds, which be moſt effectual to aboliſh all paine due to ſin, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt profitable to thoſe poore ſoules, both when they are giuen to any ſort of poore men, &amp; moſt of all when they are giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe, who are voluntarily poore, as all religious both men &amp; women are: for they will be ſure to pray deuoutly for the dead. So that they receaue a double benefit, both by the guift of the almes it ſelfe, which is a worke highly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory, and alſo by the prayers of thoſe to whom the almes are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, who often are very great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of almighty God, and their prayers moſt powerfull with him.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:42934:65"/>
Hence is that excellent aduice of <hi>S. Ambroſe l.</hi> 1. <hi>de fide &amp; reſurrect.</hi> who exhorteth the Parents to beſtow the portions which they intended to haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their children which now are dead, in almesdeeds for the reliefe of their ſoules. Excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo is that Counſell which ſome giue to rich men: They aduiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as often as they heare a poore man knocking at their doore, to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine themſelues to heare the voyce of a poore ſoule in Purgatory beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for reliefe: and if they haue any mercy in them, this imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will ſtir them vp to beſtow ſome ſmal almes both for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall reliefe of the ſoule in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and the corporal reliefe of their poore neighbour.</p>
               <p n="10">10. How grateful to God and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to the giuer thoſe almes are, which are beſtowed vpon the ſoules in Purgatory, or vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others for their reliefe, will appeare by a ſtrange example, which I haue read
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:42934:65"/>
in ſeueral Authors, of one <hi>Euſebius</hi> Duke of <hi>Sardinia.</hi> This good duke was ſo deuoted to the ſoules in Purgatory, that he beſtowed all the tithes of his Dukedome in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſes, Almesdeeds, and other pious workes for their deliuery; and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouer gaue one of his beſt Citties (which was therfore called the Citty of God) with all the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news therof, to be employed for the ſame end. It hapned that <hi>Ostor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> Duke of <hi>Sicily,</hi> being at warres with this <hi>Euſebius,</hi> ſurprized this Citty. The newes wherof being brought to <hi>Euſebius</hi> he was ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the loſſe, that he proteſted he had rather haue loſt halfe his Dukedome, and ſo with all ſpeed drawing his men togeather (which were but a handfull in regard of the enemy) marched boldly on to recouer the ſame. In the way his Scoutes diſcouered a great Army approaching with armour, horſes, banners, all as white as ſnow; at
<pb facs="tcp:42934:66"/>
which report the Duke was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtroken, yet reflecting better on the matter, conceyued hope of good from that ioyfull colour. Wherfore ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding out foure choice men to learne who they were, and what they intended; they were anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered by foure more of the white army coming to meet them, that they need not feare, for they were ſouldiers of the King of Heauen, friends to <hi>Euſebius,</hi> &amp; Enemyes to his Enemy. The Duke was much comforted with this anſwere and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> therupon riding in perſon towards the army was preſently met, and kindly ſaluted by ſome of them, who confirmed what had bin ſaid before, bidding him feare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but march on with his army after theirs. So he did. Then the white army, which ſeemed to be 40. thouſand ſtrong, making a ſtand neere to the camp of <hi>Ostor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> came preſently to a parley, &amp; gaue him to vnderſtand that they
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:42934:66"/>
were the ſouldiers of the King of Heauen ſent to reuenge the iniuſt ſurpriſall of that Citty belonging to their Maiſter, and to put <hi>Euſebius</hi> againe in poſſeſſion, adding with all ſuch threats, that <hi>Ostorgius</hi> was extremely terrifyed, &amp; humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded peace, promiſing all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſatisfaction. By this tyme <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> was come vp, to whom <hi>Ostor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> readily offered to reſtore the double of what he had taken, and to make himſelfe, and his people tributary vnto him. Theſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being agreed vpon, <hi>Euſebius</hi> applyed himſelf to the white Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my with ſuch ſignes of gratitude as were fitting in that occaſion, and then beginning to inquire more particularly what they were, had for anſwere, that they were all ſoules deliuered by his pious libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality out of Purgatory: ſo that he had iuſt cauſe of much content in what he had done, and of encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement to proceed in thoſe chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:42934:67"/>
workes, by which doubtles many more ſoules would be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out of that place of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: &amp; then taking a kind leaue, they returned the ſame way they came. [<hi>Spec. Exempl. tit. Defuncti. exemplo 25. Pinellus de altera vita l. 1. c.</hi> 28. <hi>De Bonniers in Aduocat. Anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. c. 2. Histor. Sardiniae, &amp; alij.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="11">11. We need not doubt but <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> was vnſpeakably co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted in this ſtrange occurrence, and muſt needs increaſe in deuotion &amp; libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality towards the ſoules, which he found by experience to be ſo mindfull of paying, and ouerpay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their debts. And I pray God others who haue bags of gold, and whole Lordſhips to caſt away at Dice and Cards, and waſt in braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Epicurean feaſting, may learne by this example, &amp; by what hath bin ſaid before, rather to ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their riches hereafter with aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of getting a hundred for one, then with mighty probability of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:42934:67"/>
thouſands for nothing, and their owne ſoules into the bargay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. I wiſh alſo that wealthy Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts would giue care and credit to the exhortation of <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> cited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this Chapter; which doing, they will certainly be aſhamed to beſtow more thouſands vpon a Daughter wedding to the world, then hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreds on another chooſing Chriſt for her ſpouſe. And if they had read, and pondered well the complaint made by <hi>S. Austin (l.</hi> 2. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 13.) of his owne Father, I belieue they wold make a ſcruple to be ſo cloſe-handed in breeding their ſonnes to learning &amp; vertue, and ſo very prodigall in contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to vayne, and ſometimes vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious courſes. If God, &amp; his Saints be ſo liberall, and louing to men; how vngratefull, and ill-natured are thoſe men, who deale ſo nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardly with God, and with the ſoules of Saints crying out for help in the fiery flames of Purgatory?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:42934:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> Of Indulgences.</head>
               <p n="1">1. AMongſt the meanes of relieuing the ſoules in Purgatory, one of the chiefeſt is, to gaine ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences for them as are ſo gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that they may be applyed vnto them. Now becauſe eyther for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this poynt (which is not ſo eaſily vnderſtood) or for dulnes of beliefe in it, (becauſe we, who are ſo bad, are hard to belieue God ſhould be ſo good) very many are lamentably negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in the vſe of ſo great a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; I haue thought conuenient to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle briefly this poynt, which indeed is neceſſary to be declared, to ſolue the obiection made in the 12. Chapter.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the perfect vnderſtanding of this matter, we muſt call to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:42934:68"/>
mind that, which hath bin ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proued before in the 2. Chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, how that after any ſinne is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, there doth commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne ſome guilt of paine due to ſo foule a crime. Well then, the grant of an indulgence is the grant of the remiſſion of this paine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning after the ſinne is forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which grant is communicated vnto vs to ſupply graciouſly our want of due ſatisfaction by apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſuperabundant ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Chriſt our Lord, which by his Vicar on earth are to this end ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed vnto vs, by the performance commonly of ſome worke enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs for gayning of this indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p n="3">3. So that you ſee here ariſe three things to be explicated. Firſt that the ſatisfactions of Chriſt are ſo ſuperabundant, that they are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſupply any want of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, which any man, or men can haue. Secondly, that there is a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:42934:69"/>
of Chriſt on earth, who hath lawfull power to apply theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant ſatisfactions of Chriſt for the ſupply of any want of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, which we may be in. Thirdly, ſomthing alſo muſt be declared of the things, which by Chriſts Vicar vſe to be inioyned, that thoſe ſatisfactions of Chriſt may be applyed in this manner vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Firſt then, that the ſatisfactions of Chriſt are ſo ſuperabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant that they may be a cauſe ſufficient to ſupply any, though neuer ſo great want of ſatisfactions, is eaſily gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all, and cleare of it ſelfe, if we do but reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that the bloud of Chriſt was the bloud of God, &amp; conſequently of ſo ineſtimable worth and value that the ſhedding of one only drop of it was an act abundantly ſatisfactory for the ſins of a whole world. Now then, our Sauiour ſhedding this his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinely-pretious bloud, not by
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:42934:69"/>
ſmall drops, but powring it forth by plentifull ſhowres, did heape vp an immenſe treaſure of ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſuperabundantly ſufficient to ſatisfy for any paynes due to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinne, or ſins whatſoeuer; for elſe our offences might haue bin greater then his ſatisfactions: there wanteth not therfore a cauſe euen ſuperabundantly ſufficient, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply any poſſible want of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which any man can be in, ſo infinite a treaſure is this.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Secondly, there is in the Church lawfull power and authority to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to ſuch as want ſatisfactions, theſe ſuperabundant ſatisfactions of Chriſt: for otherwiſe this infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite treaſure of the ſuperabundant ſatisfactions of Chriſt our Lord, heaped vp for vs, and for vs only, would be wholy vnprofitable to vs &amp; merely ſuperfluous. It would be like the treaſure which that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretch in <hi>S. Luke</hi> did keep lapped vp in his handkercher; or
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:42934:70"/>
the talent which that other in <hi>S. Matthew</hi> hid in the ground. Now as the holy Scripture ſaith; <hi>A hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den wiſdome, and an vnſeene treaſure what profit is there in eyther of them? Eccl.</hi> 41.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Wherefore, that this treaſure may profit vs, as it is ſuperabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, there muſt be left on earth power to diſpence forth out of this ſuperabundancy, as much as our neceſſities may require. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, to whom ſhould we thinke this power to haue byn giuen, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to him, to whome it was ſaid <hi>Joan.</hi> 20. <hi>Feed my sheepe:</hi> rather then to him to whom it was ſaid <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. <hi>To thee I will giue the keyes of the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> For it is all one to haue the keyes of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to haue authority to remoue the barre of the locke, which ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth heauen doore; ſuch a barre as ſinne is, not fully ſatisfied for: I would know, I ſay, in whome we ſhould put this power, if not in
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:42934:70"/>
him? for to him the words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing do clearly giue this commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Whatſoeuer thou shalt looſe on earth shall be looſened alſo in Heauen.</hi> Marke that word, <hi>Whatſoeuer,</hi> that is, what thing ſoeuer it be which can bind a Soule, whether it be guilt of ſinne, or guilt of paine due to ſinne, if thou doſt looſen this band on earth, it ſhalbe looſened in heauen. This was a promiſe, which doubtles Chriſt, who alwayes made good his word, did perfectly keep.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Out of this which we haue ſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> this conuincing argument may be taken. There is power left in the Church to forgiue ſinne it ſelfe, which doth deſerue the paines we ſpeake of; therfore it is no wonder that there ſhould be power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue the ſuffering of theſe paines. That there is power left to forgiue ſins the text of Scripture doth lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally affirme. The Proteſtant if he ſtandeth to the words of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture hath not a word to ſay: He
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:42934:71"/>
muſt fly to his owne expoſition of the Word; which expoſition why ſhould any man in prudence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, rather then the expoſition of the moſt learned, and moſt holy Fathers of the Primitiue Church, who ſtudyed the Scriptures day &amp; night, and may be farre more pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly thought to haue vnderſtood them aright, then thoſe who liue in an age ſo farre from Chriſt, intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with ſo many vncertaine opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, or rather certaine errours?</p>
               <p n="8">8. If the Proteſtants tell vs, they were men, and might erre, we will defire them to remember that they are alſo men, and at leaſt as likly to erre as they were. If the Proteſtant ſayth he followeth Scripture; the playne words of Scripture are cleer againſt him in this point, which is a point fundamentall concerning the forgiuenes of ſin, a thing who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary to ſaluation. That the Fathers teach, Prieſts to haue power of forgiuing ſin, I will ſhew
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:42934:71"/>
in a word. S. Chryſologus <hi>Serm.</hi> 84. writing vpon thoſe wordes, <hi>Whoſe ſins you forgiue shall be forgiuen them,</hi> ſayth thus: <hi>Where be thoſe men that affirme ſins cannot be forgiuen by men vnto men? Peter doth forgiue ſins, and with all ioy doth receiue the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; &amp; he imbraceth this power gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God vnto all Prieſts.</hi> S. <hi>Leo</hi> the Great writeth thus <hi>Ep.</hi> 91. <hi>ad Theo. Chriſt Ieſus gaue this power to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the Church, that by the doore of reconciliation they should ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to the communion of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments being now purged.</hi> But what more cleare then that of S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>de ſacerd. initio? Jt was only lawfull to the Prieſts of the Jewes to cleanſe, or (to ſpeake more truly) not to cleanſe, but to approue as cleanſed, the leproſy of the body: But to our Priests it was granted, not to cleanſe the leproſy of the body, but it was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them, I do not ſay to approue for cleanſed, but throughly to cleanſe the filth of the ſoule.</hi> Heere you ſee
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:42934:72"/>
condemned, in as cleere words as can be ſpoken, the errour of the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, who ſay that the power of our Prieſts is to declare our ſins forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and not to forgiue them: but S. Chryſoſtome ſayth, that he doth not ſay this: <hi>J do not ſay, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue for cleanſed, but throughly to cleanſe the filth of the ſoule.</hi> This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proued, let vs proceed.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If Chriſts Vicar vpon earth hath power to forgiue the ſins which did deſerue eternall paine, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to looſen the band of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall paines, can it ſeeme much that he ſhould haue power to loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the bands of temporall paine with which the ſinner is tyed after his ſins are remitted? The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſurely would ſeeme the greater wonder. Yet becauſe (&amp; ſo I come to declare the third point which I vndertook concerning the thing inioyned to be performed for the gaining of Indulgences) becauſe, I ſay, all power giuen by Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:42934:72"/>
his Vicar, is well ordered, and granted for the edification, not for the deſtruction of the Church, this authority of diſpenſing the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Chriſts ſuperabundant ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions was giuen ſo, that it might be diſpenſed forth, with prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t liberality, not powred out with lauiſhing prodigality. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all Proteſtants &amp; Catholicks are to vnderſtand, that our moſt eſteemed Deuines in this age are of opinion, that it is not in the power of the Pope to grant an Indulgence for the performance of a good worke ſo litle, that it cannot be a proportionable cauſe to grant this fauour. As for example (&amp; it is the example of S. Bonauenture, 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 20. <hi>q.</hi> 6.) to grant a great ſinner a plenary Indulgence, for giuing an Almes of three halfe pence.</p>
               <p n="10">10. But it is exceedingly to be marked, that when the Pope gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a great Indulgence, which may be obtayned by doing of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:42934:73"/>
ſomething, perhaps as ſmall as gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing an Almes of three halfe pence, the reaſon of the grant of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence is not meerly that ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle a good worke ſhould be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: for then (as S. Bonauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth) it would be an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent, and an impoſſible grant; but the reaſon of the grant of ſuch an Indulgence is the obteyning of ſome very great good, and a good ſo great (for this <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to require,) that the obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it maketh more to Gods glory, &amp; is more gratefull to him, then it would be to haue our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen ſins puniſhed in Purgatory with due rigour of iuſtice. For example ſuch a good would be the conuerſion of Infidels, Extirpation of Hereſies, conſtant Peace in the Church of God, the notable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of ſome great, or ſome neceſſary act of piety, fayth, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Charity &amp;c. The obteyning of ſuch goods as theſe, is the thing
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:42934:73"/>
which moueth the Pope to grant theſe Indulgences, and to diſpenſe forth the treaſure committed vnto him by Chriſt, for the greater glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt, which is a very pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and well-ordered diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for ſo thoſe who are put in charge with others goods do moſt faithfully exerciſe their charge, if they lay them out for the greater benefit of thoſe who did put them in truſt.</p>
               <p n="11">11. I ſee well, that it will be obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that though the Pope doth piouſly and prudently to imploy the treaſure committed to his charge for obteyning of a greater good, yet it ſeeemeth that he doth imprudently to vſe, for obteyning of it, ſuch an vnproportionable, &amp; vnfit meanes, as is to inioyne only the performance of a good worke ſo little, to be done for this end; as for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, to inioyne only the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 5. <hi>Pater Nosters</hi> for obteining ſo great a good as is the Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:42934:74"/>
of Infidels, extirpation of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies &amp;c. And therfore though the cauſe of this Grant be reaſonable, yet the meanes applyed ſeeme moſt vnreaſonable. I anſwere, that the performance of ſo little a good worke, as is the ſaying of fiue <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Nosters,</hi> for obteyning the good for which the Indulgence is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, may be a very effectual meanes for obteyning of ſo great a good. Which that I may ſhew, let vs but conſider what doth dayly happen, when the Pope granteth ſuch an Indulgence as this is. The grant of this Indulgence is no ſooner made knowne vnto the Church, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently you ſhall ſee all faythfull people, by thouſands, with one heart, and one ſoule, doing that which is neceſſary for gaining of this Indulgences: that is, by a true, entire, and harty Confeſſion and contrition putting themſelues (if they feare they were not in it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) in ſtate of grace, and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:42934:74"/>
with God, and then after this (for this muſt be done for gaining of Indulgences) deuoutly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the good worke inioyned them to be performed and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it to the end, for which it was inioyned. Now, though this good worke be but little, though it be but the ſaying of fiue <hi>Pater Noſters</hi> for the foreſayd intention; yet when euen ſo few praiers are ſayd with one heart, and one ſoule, by ſo many thouſands of thouſands, as vſe (by the grant of ſo great an Indulgence exacting only the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of ſo ſmall a worke) to be ſtirred vp to the deuout recitall of theſe prayers, the quantity of all theſe prayers put together, amou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to an immenſe ſumme, a ſumme ſo great, and made vp by ſuch an vniforme deuotion of ſo many faythfull people, that it may in prudence be thought to be a meanes ſufficient to effect the good intended.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:42934:75"/>12. Hence it appeareth that the performance of a little thing may be an effectuall meanes to obtaine a great good, when by the exacting of a thing ſo ſmall, euery body is inuited to do what is neceſſary to the perfect performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of it; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if they were inuited by a ſmall Indulgence, or by a great one which could not be gained but by ſome great good worke, as faſting many dayes, ſaying many prayers &amp;c. very few would be induced to gaine this Indulgence. And ſo it may well happen, that Chriſts Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcarce vſe any meanes more effectuall to obtaine a good which maketh ſo much to Gods glory &amp; the benefit of his Church, then by granting ſome great Indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which may be gained, by doing ſome ſmall good worke for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. For it is very likely that a farre greater quantity of good works will be rayſed, whileſt eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one contributeth a little, then
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:42934:75"/>
when almoſt euery body layeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all care of doing any thing, becauſe without he doth a great deale, he is neuer the neerer, for as much as concerneth the gaining of the Indulgence. We vſe to ſay, t'is well for poore men that braſſe far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things goe currently, for now eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body coms eaſily off with a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, wheras their charity would hardly be great inough to part with a penny.</p>
               <p n="13">13. All which we haue ſaid, hath farre leſſe difficulty when an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence is granted, to bring in publicke practiſe ſome important act of piety, or to hinder decay of ſome great deuotion, eſpecially of ſome vertue neceſſary to ſaluation, as Fayth, Charity, Contrition &amp;c. Becauſe in this caſe not only all theſe things do make more to Gods glory, then that ordinary ſeuerity of puniſhing by the paines of Purgatory; but it is eaſily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood how theſe ſo important
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:42934:76"/>
things may effectually be procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the performance of things but ſmall in themſelues, though great in their effects. For example, it is a thing moſt important, that all faythfull people ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe vnion with their ſupreme Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, and alſo the decay of this v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is much to be feared, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the power of Hereſy. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine this vnion may be effectually brought into great requeſt by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſometimes in a yeare ſome publick and ſolemne profeſſion of it, which may be done by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly to receyue his benediction in ſome great feſtiuity: therfore the Pope both may, &amp; doth moſt piouſly and prudently in granting a great Indulgence for performing an act in it ſelfe ſo eaſy and little, as is to aske his benediction.</p>
               <p n="14">14. In like ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner true faith, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> is loſt by obſtinately reiecting the authority of the Church,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:42934:76"/>
though in matters otherwiſe of no exceeding great conſequence, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the maintayning of faith in all ſuch matters, when there is danger of the loſſe of it, maketh very much to Gods glory, and the good of ſoules. Now, the pious beliefe of theſe points ſo important may ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficaciouſly be vpholden, &amp; broght into publick practiſe and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the practice of ſome acts, which are moſt eaſily performed: for example ſake, Prayer for the dead, veneration of Reliques, gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Indulgences, are points of faith, which Hereticks ſeeke by all meanes to ouerthrow. Againe, they may be efficaciouſly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in a continuall; and moſt deuout practice, if the Pope would grant ſome great Indulgence for making ſome frequent pious acts, which may reuiue theſe deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and keep the practice of them in dayly vſe.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Now, to ſtop in a word the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:42934:77"/>
mouths of Proteſtants, which are ſo wide open to cry downe theſe Indulgences, I will onely put them in mind of their owne Doctrine. They ſay, <hi>A man is iuſtified by faith onely;</hi> in ſo much that if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were as great a ſinner as could be, yet this man if be would but make one act of true Faith, ſhould be in a moment iuſtifyed, &amp; not ſo much as lyable to the leaſt puniſhment for all his innumerable and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſins. Is any pardon, Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, or Iubily ſo eaſely obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or ſo incredible as this? Do but belieue (which will not paine your bones the leaſt) &amp; All, All, though it were a thouſand times more, is wholy forgiuen you; And ſinne as much to morrow, (if it be poſſible) as you haue ſinned in all the dayes of your life, and you ſhall not ceaſe for all this to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, if you do not ceaſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, which (as they ſay) you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ceaſe to do. Was there euer the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:42934:77"/>
like deuiſe to make wide the ſtrait gate of heauen? Wheras if you will obtaine a Catholick Indulgence, <hi>First you must</hi> belieue: but this is not all, as it is with Proteſtants: <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly you must</hi> haue true hope: <hi>Thirdly you muſt</hi> be in perfect Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and in the ſtate of grace, and conſequently <hi>you must</hi> haue had true and hearty repentance of all your ſins: <hi>you must</hi> haue a firme purpoſe to forſake them; <hi>you must</hi> haue made an entire and contrite confeſſion of them; <hi>you must,</hi> if you haue wronged any man, haue made him due ſatisfaction; and after all this, <hi>you must</hi> do the thing which is required for obteyning of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence; which (though in ſome occaſions it be little) yet many times it is the faſt of three dayes, the viſiting of Churches, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout praying in them, the giuing of Almes &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="16">16. And all this being duely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that which is wanting to
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:42934:78"/>
the full ſatisfaction of the paine due to your forgiuen ſins, ſhalbe gratiouſly ſupplyed by the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundant ſatisfactions of Chriſt our Lord, applyed by his Vicar vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you to this end; So that, euen after all this, no one ſin is by the Indulgence forgiuen you: for all Catholicks teach, that all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences in the world cannot forgiue the leaſt mortall ſin, no nor veniall, as moſt affirme; but all that is forgiuen by way of Indulgence is the paine to which the ſinner was lyable, euen after his ſin was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen him. And therfore if the ſin remaine ſtill vnforgiuen, the paine due vnto it cannot by any Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence be forgiuen. And this is a great reaſon why ſo few do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a perfect plenary Indulgence of all that paine which they were liable vnto, becauſe there be but few who vſe due diligence to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure all their ſins euen veniall to be fully forgiuen them, and therfore
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:42934:78"/>
they do not obteine the remiſſion of the payne due to thoſe ſinnes which remaine vnforgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though they obteyne the remiſſion of the paine due to all which are forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. The importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath made me more to enlarge my ſelfe then I intended.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Two other meanes of higher Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by which we may relieue the Soules in Purgatory.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe firſt is, to offer vp all our good actions, thoughts, words, and ſufferings, deſiring God to accept of them for the reliefe of ſuch a Soule or Soules in Purgatory; to offer them vp all, I ſay, as they are ſatisfactory, for ſo they do eyther onely or chiefly profit them; and ſo we remayne free to apply the ſame workes, as they are impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:42934:79"/>
for obteyning any thing we deſire to pray for: yet I would not haue this ſo vnderſtood, as though we were not in the firſt place to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy any obligation which perhaps we might haue of employing ſome part of our works for other inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Neither would I aduiſe any man to performe the pennances enioyned him in confeſſion, for ſatisfaction of the ſins of any other beſides himſelfe. But out of theſe or ſuch like caſes, I know not how we can better apply our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as they are ſatisfactory: for thus all our actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are not leſſe but more meritorious, not leſſe but more impetratory, not leſſe but more ſatisfactory: Thus we may hope to eſcape all, or the greateſt part of Purgatory paynes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not againſt charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our ſelues to be thus libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. All theſe things haue bin pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the former chapters.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A man would thinke it were
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:42934:79"/>
not poſſible to proceed any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this charitable deuotion. But Charity is ſo witty in her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, that ſhe hath found out a way to giue more then ſhe hath, or euer had in this life. You ſhall ſee this verified in a ſtrange man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, and an vnheard of example, which cannot be well vnderſtood, without we firſt let all know that whenſoeuer any one dyeth in the Society of Ieſus, euen the meaneſt Brother in the houſe, it is ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Conſtitutions of the ſame Society, that all of that houſe, where the party deceaſeth, who are Prieſts, are to ſay three Maſſes for his ſoule, &amp; thoſe who are not Prieſts three payre of bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and throughout the whole Prouince (which many times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of ſeauen, or eight hundred perſons) euery Prieſt is to ſay two Maſſes, and each one of the reſt two payre of beades for the ſame intention. And beſides all theſe
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:42934:80"/>
prayers euery Prieſt of our Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty throughout the whole world is obliged euery weeke to ſay one Maſſe, and ech one of thoſe who are not Prieſts, one paire of beades for thoſe of their Order deceaſed out of their particular Prouinces; for if the deceaſed be of the ſame Prouince, then they are to ſay for them two a peece, as eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now hath bin ſaid. Hence it appeareth, that there dyeth not any one in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, for whom a very great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Maſſes, and prayers are not ſaid. Let vs put a probable ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: Suppoſe there be ſixteene thouſand perſons in the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ety, &amp; that one halfe of this number be Prieſts, the reſt either Students, Nouices, or lay-Brothers: Let vs alſo ſuppoſe, that taking one week with another, there dy out of this number foure a weeke. This ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, it followeth that euery one of theſe foure ſhall haue for his part alone, neere two thouſand
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:42934:80"/>
Maſſes, and as many payre of bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſaid for his ſoule, out of the Prouince where he dyed, beſides thoſe which are ſaid for him in the Houſe, and Prouince in which he dyed. This being ſo, heare now a rare act of Charity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Father Ferdinand Monroy</hi> of the Society of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> a man of rare ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity, when he came to dye, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in that houre liuely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending, what Comfort he might take in the multitude of Maſſes, &amp; prayers which he knew ſhould after his death be ſaid for his ſoule, according to the rule of his Order, was notwithſtanding ſo inflamed with ardent charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſoules of his, &amp; Chriſts brethren ſuffering in Purgatory, that he bequeathed vnto them by Will &amp; Teſtament all the Maſſes, and other prayers, which after his departure ſhould be offered vp for his ſoule; and ſo departed this life eyther directly towards heauen (as
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:42934:81"/>
is moſt probable) or a wellcome gueſt to the ſoules in Purgatory. <hi>(Euſeb. Nierembergicus tract. de Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorio.)</hi> Can charity proceed any further? Let then the imitation of this example be a ſecond meanes for them whoſe charity burnes ſo much hoater then Purgatory. If a third meanes of relieuing theſe ſoules, perfecter then this could be found, yet all that could be done, ought not to ſeeme too much, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is done for Chriſts ſake, for his brethren, for ſoules ſo eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by him, that what is done for them, he taketh it as done vnto himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If any demand whether theſe two deuotions may be ſecurely practiſed by all kind of men, what quality ſoeuer they be of? I anſwer that they may, with great profit of their owne, and their neighbours ſoules, and aduancement of Gods glory, if for more caution this condition be added: <hi>As far as it is
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:42934:81"/>
ſutable to Gods holy will, and maketh to the greatest increaſe of his glory, I offer vp, for the reliefe of the ſoules in Purgatory, the whole ſatisfactory ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of whatſoeuer good I shall do, or euill J shall ſuffer, all the time of my whole life, and all the prayers &amp; other good works whatſoeuer which shalbe performed for me after my death; ſo far I ſay, as this shalbe moſt pleaſing to God.</hi> For what danger can there be in this Act? Can that be any way ſubiect to be done amiſſe, which is wholy ſubiected to the diuine wil? Two extreames might be dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in that which concernes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion for the ſoules in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: The firſt, by ſhewing them too little charity: the ſecond, by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting wel-ordered Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our ſelues, and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours heere on earth. As for the firſt, this charity cannot be to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, becauſe we do for the ſoules as great a part of our actions as God would haue vs, for we offer them
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:42934:82"/>
all, ſo far as is moſt agreable to his holy will: &amp; as for the ſecond we forget not to reſerue as great a part of our workes for our ſelues, and our neighbours on earth, as God would haue vs; for we giue away no more then beſt pleaſeth him, and maketh moſt to his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt honour. So that I cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the leaſt ſhadow of danger in practiſing theſe deuotions in the manner aboue ſaid, for would any man do more for himſelfe, or leſſe for theſe poore ſoules, then God would haue him?</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Reuerend Father <hi>Euſebius Nierembergicus,</hi> in a Treatiſe be wrote of Purgatory, did handle this point ſo well, that two wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Doctours and Profeſſours of Diuinity at <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently examining the force of his reaſons, were ſo conuinced ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that both of them, together with diuers of their ſchollers gaue all the ſatisfactions of their whole
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:42934:82"/>
life to the ſoules in Purgatory. <hi>(Libell. de modo ſe citò ditandi.)</hi> This deuotion in fine hath bin practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by many great ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God, highly recommended for their pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by moſt graue Authours; and God did reward <hi>S. Gertrude</hi> for it in that liberal manner before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned: and if it be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſed with the caution now ſpoken of, no man can ſuſpect it, neither can there be any want of deuotion in adding a condition ſo pious.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP XVI.</hi> To what Soules in Purgatory we are chiefly to apply our ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory works.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I know not how to begin this Chapter better, then by anſwering an obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſome ſpeculatiue witty may chance to ſtumble at. Alas, will ſome ſay, what good, will all my
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:42934:83"/>
poore works do, when they come to be ſhared among ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſoules as be in Purgatory? They wilbe like a little loafe of bread amongſt a great multitude of beggars, which if it be equally cut, euery one will ſcarce receyue a crumme. Theſe men ſeeme to ſuppoſe themſelues the onely men in the world who ſhew charity to the ſoules in Purgatory. For if there be others (and many others) who by Gods grace are no leſſe charitable and liberall then they, it is not hard to vnderſtand how by the helpe of many, many may be holpen. That which <hi>Thomas,</hi> or <hi>William</hi> doth contribute towards the maintenance of a whole army, will not affoard euery Souldier a farthing; and yet becauſe others in great multitudes contribute as well as they, whole armyes are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily maintayned in a flouriſhing eſtate. So whileſt many deuout ſoules relieue theſe helpleſſe ſoules
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:42934:83"/>
many helpleſſe ſoules are relieued.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And indeed we haue great reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſhew charity to all: For firſt the law of Nature cryeth out vnto vs: <hi>All things that you would men should do to you, do you alſo to them. Matth.</hi> 7. Secondly, the written Law in playne termes ſaith: <hi>Loue thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelfe.</hi> Thirdly, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour addeth a ſtrange force alſo to this Precept: <hi>This is my precept, that you loue one an other as J haue lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued you. Ioan. 15.</hi> Now how he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs, all his life, and moſt of all his bleſſed death doth teſtify. Fourthly, all ſoules are ſo eſteemed by Chriſt, that he taketh that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which is ſhewed to the leaſt of them as kindly as if it were done to himſelfe in perſon. In fine the vertue of Mercy calles vpon vs to aſſiſt all who are in extreame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, as theſe poore ſoules are. Theſe be forcible reaſons mouing vs to aſſiſt al that be in Purgatory.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet it is in no caſe to be miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:42934:84"/>
but it is rather a moſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable deuotion to pray for ſome ſoules in particular, and in the firſt place for thoſe, to which, beſides thoſe generall reaſons now alleaged for all, we may haue ſome peculiar obligation. For ſome we may be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to pray by our owne oath, promiſe, compact, rule &amp;c. For others by the vertue of Piety, as our Parents, ſpirituall Fathers, kindred, frends, and acquaintance &amp;c. For ſome againe out of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, as our benefactours ſpirituall &amp; temporall &amp;c. Theſe reaſons be more particular, and therfore they ought to preuayle more with vs, then thoſe other generall reaſons, for which we are to pray for all men, becauſe the generall reaſons make as much for theſe as for any others, and beſides they haue alſo their particular reaſons.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But when we know not ſuch particular reaſons as theſe are, yet it wilbe piouſly done, to pray for
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:42934:84"/>
ſome ſoules in particular, though in a manner more generall: for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, for that ſoule whoſe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery maketh moſt to Gods glory, whoſe reliefe, or releaſement the glorious Virgin Mary moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, for thoſe who were moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted to her, for thoſe who be in greateſt neceſsity, moſt of all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne &amp;c. For thoſe who are ſo neere their deliuery, that by our ſmall deuotions they may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſet free, and conſequently immediately glorify God, pray for vs &amp;c. In fine here euery man may do what is moſt ſutable to his priuate deuotion, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is beſt, when it is ordered by the moſt perfect rule of Gods greater glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:42934:85"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> The perfect practiſe of all contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this Booke.</head>
               <p n="1">1. VVHoſoeuer to Gods glory, the good of his owne ſoule, and reliefe of thoſe in Purgatory, deſireth to put in practiſe all which hath bin treated of in this booke; muſt firſt aboue all things haue a care to put and keep himſelfe in ſtate of grace, for if he hath not the grace and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God, though he ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute all his ſubſtance to the poore, or all his works to the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in Purgatory, it would profit him, and them nothing at all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, he muſt not ſlubber ouer this deuotion in a careles ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, giuing his works away, and little marking why, or what he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues: but he muſt take ſome ſhort
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:42934:85"/>
time to conſider the Motiues ſet downe in this Treatiſe, and muſt ponder ech motiue by it ſelfe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his will be ſtirred vp effectually to affoard all reliefe he is able to the diſtreſſed ſoules. Neither is this any long buſines, becauſe euen the reading attentiuely theſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, is ſufficient to moue any heart to helpe ſuch help-les ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: and this is the thing we deſire, for we little regard the being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to a ſoft and tender compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which God know's is often very fruitles, and ſoone vaniſheth away.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Wherfore that all may performe this with little or no difficulty, we will ſet downe in playne and full words the manner of making per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly all thoſe acts, which in any part of this Treatiſe haue bin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended. But let no man thinke vnles he would make a meditation of this matter (as he may do with great fruit in the ſpace of halfe an
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:42934:86"/>
houre) that we would haue him make all theſe acts at one time, but rather that he exerciſe now one, now another, more or fewer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his leaſure and deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yet it wilbe beſt to exerciſe often the moſt perfect. Now, for the Readers commodity, we will cite the Chapters, where the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are treated at large, which here are only touched in a word.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The firſt Act anſwerable to the third, fourth, &amp; fifth Chapter may be thus made: O how exceſſiue is the bitterneſſe of thoſe paynes which theſe afflicted ſoules do ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in Purgatory! What a miſery is it to be baniſhed (though for a time only) from the face of God! In what a ſea of affliction muſt that poore ſoule be, which for a long ſpace is condemned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in this pittifull ſtate! <hi>Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O my Soule, affoard theſe ſoules of thy Brethren all help thou canst: Pray for them, exerciſe acts of pennance for
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:42934:86"/>
them; procure the holy Sacrifice of Maſſe may be offred for them; giue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes that they may be prayed for: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue them by all Indulgences which may be gayned for them; let all thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory actions and ſufferings of thy whole life be offered vp for them, ſo far as it is ſutable to Gods holy will; &amp; ſo far as it maketh to his greater glory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the good workes which after thy departure out of this life shalbe done for thee. O Lord accept of this my most harty oblation, made in behalfe of my distreſſed Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Act, anſwerable to the ſixt Chapter <hi>n.</hi> 2. O my God how great is thy Excellency, Worth, and Perfection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> All honour and glory is due vnto thee. <hi>I poore cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature know not how more perfectly to procure thy diuine Maieſty to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, honoured, and glorifyed, then by doing al I am able, to deliuer ſome ſoule or ſoules, which being releaſed by my meanes from Purgatory, may honour, prayſe and glorify thy ſacred Maieſty
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:42934:87"/>
in the highest manner. Wherfore O my Soule, to this end affoard theſe ſoules of thy Brethren all the help thou canſt: Pray for them &amp;c.</hi> as it followeth in the former Act.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The third Act, anſwerable alſo to the ſixt Chapter <hi>nu.</hi> 3. O moſt mercifull, liberall, &amp; good God, how many, &amp; how great benefits, haſt thou with vnſpeakable loue heaped vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me! How ſhall I be able to requite this thy bounty, mercy and goodnes! <hi>I poore Creature know not how more perfectly to procure thy diuine Maiesty &amp;c.</hi> all as followeth in the ſecond Act.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The fourth Act, anſwerable to the ſixt Chapter <hi>n.</hi> 4. How many &amp; how enormous haue bin the ſins, by which I haue diſhonoured thee my good God! Thee, O infinite Excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy! Thee O imme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes! <hi>I poore Creature know not how more perfectly to procure thy diuine Maiesty &amp;c.</hi> as before, in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Act.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:42934:87"/>8. The fifth Act, anſwerable to the ſixt Chapter alſo, <hi>nu.</hi> 5. O my deare Ieſus, thou loueſt the ſoules of my Brethren ſo dearely, that whatſoeuer for thy ſake is done vnto them, thou accounteſt done vnto thy ſelfe. <hi>Wherfore O my Soule to this end affoard the ſoules of thy Brethren &amp;c.</hi> as before in the firſt Act.</p>
               <p n="9">9. It is very good to renew theſe Acts often, and to make euery morning, ſome one of theſe obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: for this is a deuotion, by which we may purchaſe many great commodityes, and ſuffer no diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity; by which our works may become more meritorious, our prayers more impetratory, our actions more higly ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and finally by which we may haue great hope, to eſcape eyther all, or at leaſt a great part of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Neither is there any danger of violating Charity due to our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:42934:88"/>
by the practice of this deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but we may rather offend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt charity by making ſlight of a deuotion, which might haue bin ſo beneficiall to vs. For it is cleare we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> looſe nothing, &amp; muſt needs gaine much: much for our ſelues, much for our neighbour, &amp; much for the glory of Almighty God: to whom be all prayſe &amp; glory for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:42934:88"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A TABLE</hi> Of the Chapters of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. I.</hi> PVrgatory proued by all kind of ſacred Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. <hi>pag. 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. II.</hi> Purgatory proued by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, grounded in Scripture. <hi>pag. 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. III.</hi> The first Motiue to pray for the Soules in Purgatory, which is, the greatnes of the ſenſible paines they ſuffer. <hi>pag. 32.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. IV.</hi> The ſecond Motiue, drawne from the intollerable paynes the ſoules ſuffer, by being banished from the fight of God. <hi>pag. 44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. V.</hi> The third Motiue taken from the long tyme that theſe paynes do endure. <hi>pag. 53.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:42934:89"/>
                  <hi>Chap. VI.</hi> That for the loue we beare to God, we ought to be much moued to help the Soules in Purgatory. <hi>pag 64.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VII.</hi> That by offering our Actions for the Soules in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we purchaſe many great Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities for our ſelues, &amp; ſustaine no Incommodity. <hi>pag 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VIII.</hi> That by offering our Actions for the ſoules in Purgatory, we do not merit leſſe, but more. <hi>p 77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. IX.</hi> That our Actions offered vp for the ſoules in Purgatory, are not leſse, but more impetratory of other fauours. <hi>pag. 86.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. X.</hi> That by offering our Actions for the Soules in Purgatory, we do not leſſe, but more ſatisfy for our owne ſinnes. <hi>pag. 96.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XI.</hi> That by offering our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the Soules in Purgatory we haue great hope of eſcaping ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all, or a good part of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. <hi>pag. 104.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XII.</hi> That it is not against
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:42934:89"/>
Charity to our ſelues, to offer our Actions for the Soules in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, but it is rather against it not to offer them. <hi>pag. 112.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XIII.</hi> By what meanes we may help the Soules in Purgatory. <hi>pag. 115.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XIV.</hi> Of Jndulgences. <hi>pa. 132.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XV.</hi> Two other meanes of higher Perfection, by which we may relieue the Soules in Purgatory. <hi>pag. 153.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XVI.</hi> To what Soules in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory we are chiefly to apply our ſatisfactory workes. <hi>pag. 161.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XVII.</hi> The perfect practice of all conteynd in this Books. <hi>pag.</hi> 166.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:42934:90"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42934:90"/>
            <head>THREE AND THIRTY moſt godly &amp; deuout Prayers or Salutations, to be recited in honour of the Sacred Life &amp; Paſsion of our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſweet Ieſus, for faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soules departed: After ech wherof, must be ſaid the Pſalme, <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Preamble, or Introduction.</head>
            <p>O Moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus moſt mercifull pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our ſinnes, and Sauiour of our ſoules, we hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſeech thee, by all the mercies
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42934:91"/>
that euer thou haſt ſhewed to ſinners from the firſt inſtant of thy birth vnto this prese<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t houre, that thou wilt not refuſe the prayers of vs poore ſinners for this Soule (or theſe Soules) but be pleaſed to deliuer them from all paine, &amp; graunt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternall reſt, through thy botto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>les mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for that to ſaue vs thou didſt aſſume our poore humanity.</p>
            <div n="1" type="prayer">
               <head>THE I. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee Eternall word and wiſdome of the Father &amp; beſeech thee, by that infinite charity which drew thee from the boſome of thy eternall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to choſe the pure immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Virgin to be thy mother, as alſo through that admirable worke thou wroughteſt in her ſacred wombe, when thou didſt cloath thy Glorious Diuinity
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42934:91"/>
with our baſe fleſh, and in that ſort becameſt our brother, and dideſt giue thy glorious mother vnto vs for an Aduocate and mother, for which cauſe we hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly haue recourſe vnto her, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping what our owne merites cannot obtaine, to impetrate by her; confident wherof we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert our ſelues to thee, ô ſweet Mother of mercy, and by that ineſtimable treaſure which was incloſed in thy Virginal wombe which neither heauen nor earth could containe: O daughter of the eternall Father, mother of the ſonne, and ſpouſe of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, we beſeech thee that thou wilt vouchſafe by thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſsion to open vnto vs the ſame diuine treaſure, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thy beloued ſonne, that throgh the loue he bore thee, he will receiue our petitions for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42934:92"/>
this Soule, (or theſe Soules) and forgiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in whatſoeuer they haue offended, and by his holy birth, by which he hath broken Adams chaines, wilbe pleaſed to vnlooſe theſe poore Soules from the chaines of their ſinnes. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere mei Deus &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <head>THE II. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee O moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus, fountaine of mercy, and bright Mirrour of al vertue, &amp; beſeech thee throgh the extreme pouerty and other afflictions that thou dideſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in thy holy birth and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der infancy, as alſo by thy great humility, penance, faſting, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, praying, and other auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, that thou dideſt liuing here vpon earth for the ſpace of 33. yeares &amp; by thy painful foot-ſteps going bare-foote and bare
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42934:92"/>
head, throgh the hunger &amp; thirſt cold and heate, labour &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, &amp; the other miſeries thou ſufferedſt euery hower and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment during thy life for our ſaluation, &amp; that immenſe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity wherby thou dideſt offer all thoſe thy ſuffrings to thy cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall Father for the ſatisfaction of our ſinnes, that thou wilt mercifully pardon theſe Soules all the offences they haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited againſt thee in pride, vain-glory, couetouſnes, ſenſuality vaine cares of temporall things &amp; vanities, &amp; impure thoughtes wordes and actions, throgh the merits of all thy ſufferances &amp; labours, and moſt holy life and conuerſation. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <head>THE III. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee, ô Eternall comfort &amp; ſweet ſolace of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42934:93"/>
our ſoules, and beſeech thee by that infinite loue &amp; mercy thou haſt awayes ſhewed to ſinners, ſo immenſe that no vnderſtanding is able to comprehend it; by that loue which made thee who art an incomprehenſible treaſure to permit thy ſelfe to be ſold for thirty pence; &amp; by that infinite charity wherewith thou dideſt giue thy ſelfe in the diuine Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to thy Apoſtles vnder the ſpecies of bread and wine, &amp; to vs all as a pledge of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; through this thy liberality we beſeech thee ô bread of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Sauiour of ſoules, the giuer and the gift, that thou wilt mercifully pardon theſe Soules all the offences they haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited againſt thee by vnworthy receauing of this holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t without due contrition, right confeſſion, and entire ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42934:93"/>
forgiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ô Lord throgh thy infinite mercy. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="prayer">
               <head>THE IV. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô bread of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells and comforter of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull hartes, &amp; beſeech thee by thy profound humility with which thou didſt bow downe thy knees at thy diſciples feet &amp; waſhed them, as alſo through that holy Sermon thou dideſt make vnto them; and the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull wordes thou ſpakeſt, ſaying, My ſoule is ſorrowfull vnto death; vntil now you haue not prayed; pray, for whatſoeuer you ſhall aske the Father in my name, he will giue it you: O lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Lord, through this thy promiſe we beſeech thy bleſſed Father, through thee his only deere beloued ſonne, that he wil reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the great anxiety thy ſacred
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42934:94"/>
humanity did indure when it beheld all thoſe intollerable torments &amp; death it was to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe, &amp; by the bitter anguiſh therof we beſeech him and thy ſacred ſelfe mercifully to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don theſe Soules all they haue offended in vaine ſolace, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them into thy eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="prayer">
               <head>THE V. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lord Ieſus, ſweet ſhee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheard of our Soules, who for our redemption haſt drunke the chalice of thy bitter paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech thee by that painful agony which thou didſt willingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure when kneeling and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate on the ground thou didſt pray three ſeuerall times to thy celeſtiall Father ſaying, Father if it be poſſible let this Chalice
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42934:94"/>
paſſe from me, yet not my will but thyne be done; at which time thou dideſt ſweat water &amp; bloud, through the bitterneſſe of thy anguiſh, and an Angell came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort thee ſaying, Ariſe, go forward co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly, you ſhal appeaſe your Fathers wrath, you ſhall breake Adams bandes &amp; redeeme man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; after which thou wenteſt to thy Diſciples &amp; finding them a ſleep ſaidſt, do you ſleep now? Ariſe let vs go, for he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayeth me is at hand: O deere Lord, through that thy willing reſignation to ſuffer death, to fulfill the will of thy heauenly Father, and through thy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourous agonye and blouddy ſweat we beſeech thee mercifuly to pardon theſe poore ſoules all the offences they haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt thy diuine pleaſure
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42934:95"/>
or the Obedience of their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, and through thy holy &amp; ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prayer, receiue our hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prayers, and petitions for them. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="prayer">
               <head>THE VI. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus, &amp; beſeech thee by that inflamed charity wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou dideſt go to meet the traitor Iudas, asking him &amp; the reſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſoght, &amp; they anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wering Ieſus of Nazareth, thou anſweredſt I am he, through the power of which wordes they all fell two ſeuerall times downe to the ground; after which giuing them power to riſe thou dideſt meekly receiue the kiſſe of the traytor Iudas, ſaying to him, Friend whereto art thou come, doſt thou betray the ſonne of man with a kiſſe? We thanke
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42934:95"/>
thee, O moſt ſweet Sauiour for all theſe mercies, and beſeech thee throgh the merits of them to forgiue theſe ſoules whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they haue offended in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, murmuration, vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable friendſhip, or any other offences, &amp; beſeech thee by that infinite loue and charity wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou dideſt deſire to haue pardoned Iudas, that thou wilt haue mercy vpon theſe poore Soules, and pardon them all the ſinnes they haue committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="prayer">
               <head>THE VII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus, and repreſent vnto thee that Patience, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou dideſt ſuffer thy ſelfe to be furiouſly apprehended by the wicked Iewes, who ſeized vpon thee as thou hadſt beene
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42934:96"/>
ſome theefe, or wicked male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour, and bound thy ſacred handes ſo cruelly behind thee, that the bloud ſprung forth of thy nayles; then wert thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of all thy friendes and lefte in the cruell handes of thoſe impious and moſt inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſlaues, who pulling &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thee gaue thee many cruell buffets, ſpurnes and blowes, and in that manner led thee vnto the houſe of Annas the high Prieſt, who imperiouſly examininge thee of thy Diſciples and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, thou anſweredſt, I haue taught openly in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the people reſorte, and in ſecret I haue ſaid nothing, why askeſt thou me, aske thoſe that heard me; for which one of the ſeruantes that ſtood by gaue thee ſo cruell a blow on the race that thy teeth looſened in thy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42934:96"/>
head ſaying; anſwereſt thou the high Prieſt ſo? Others ſpurned thee, ſtrooke thee on the necke and ſpit vpon that diuine face which celeſtiall ſpirits are neuer ſatisfied to behold: O deareſt Lord Ieſus, we render infinite thankes to thy immenſe charity for all theſe thy ſufferinges, and humbly beſeech thee by them, &amp; by thoſe merciful eyes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou dideſt behold <hi>S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> that thou wilt with the ſame eye of pitty, looke vpon theſe ſoules, &amp; looſe them from all their chaines, and forgiue them all their ſinnes, through the manifold tormentes thou didſt endure that night. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="prayer">
               <head>THE VIII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Sauiour, ſole comfort of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42934:97"/>
ſinners, and repreſent vnto thee how furiouſly thoſe cruell Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers led thee bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to Cayphas, before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſtoodeſt like a meeke Lambe and heardeſt the falſe witneſſe they brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee; How thou wenteſt about to ſeduce the people, and taugheſt them falſe doctrine; That thou ſaidſt thou couldſt deſtroy the temple, &amp; in three dayes readify it: Then Cayphas adiured thee by the liuing God, to tell him if thou wert Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom thou anſweredſt, thou ſaieſt that I am; Whereupon he rent his cloathes, and ſaid, He hath blaſphemed, what need we any more witneſſes; at which they all cryed out, he is worthy of death, and furiouſly running vpon thee vnmeaſurably ſpit in thy face, buffeted and beat thee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42934:97"/>
cruelly, ſtriking thee on thy holy necke, and face, and head, blindfolding thee, and giuing thee cruell blowes, and ſaying in deriſion and ſcorne, Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy ô Chriſt who it is that ſtroke thee: for all which ſufferances, paines &amp; moſt in human iniuries we render thee infinite thankes, O moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus, and humbly beſeech thee by the merits of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to forgiue theſe ſoules if at any time they haue detracted, and through all thy tormentes pardon them what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they haue committed againſt thee. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="prayer">
               <head>THE IX. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô ſweet Ieſus almighty power &amp; in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible wiſdom of God, &amp; repreſent vnto thee how theſe raging dogges led thee furiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42934:98"/>
vnto Pilate, demaunding the ſentence of death againſt thee, he then ſent thee to Herod who greatly reioyced at thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, hoping to haue ſeene ſome miracle wrought by thee, but thou dideſt not anſwere him one word, but ſtoodſt like a milde la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be holding thy peace, which Herode ſeeing he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee to be mocked, ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and cloathed in a white garment like a foole, ſetting in deriſion a crowne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy head and ſpiting in thy face, ſtriking thee and ſaying. All hayle king of Iſrael: After which he ſent thee back to Pilate ſaying, he thought he had ſent him a wiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaw he was a very foole O ſweet Sauiour how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> did they to thee by the way caſting ſtones and filth at thee! O eternall wiſdome of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42934:98"/>
the Father how art thou derided, how art thou defiled and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red! O deereſt Lord we render infinite thankes to thee for all theſe thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumelies, ſcornes, &amp; iniuries, and hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſeech thee by them to pardon theſe ſoules all their vnthankefulneſe, for thy bitter paſſion, and all want of charity towards their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="prayer">
               <head>THE X. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus eternall God &amp; true man, and repreſent vnto thee the great humility wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou ſtoodeſt before Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, meeke and ſilent, ready to ſuffer all ſhame and confuſion, outrages &amp; iniuries they could do againſt thee: Pilate ſaid vnto thee what haſt thou done that all the world is thus offended
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42934:99"/>
againſt thee; as alſo many other queſtions he asked thee, vnto which thou dideſt not anſwere any thing; then Pilate ſaid, he found no cauſe of death in thee; but they all cryed and exclamed againſt thee, ſaying, Thou wert a breaker of the law, &amp; calledſt thy ſelfe the ſonne of God; vnto whome thou anſweredſt, Thou haſt ſaid that I am, for this cauſe came I into the world, that I ſhould giue teſtimony of the truth; after which Pilate ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the Iewes, I find no cauſe of death in this man; but they with furious clamors ſaid He is worthy of death; Pilate then anſwered, I wil correct him and diſmiſſe him. O good Ieſus, ô ſonne of the liuing God, ô ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne king of glory we ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee infinite thankes for all theſe thy ſufferings, and humbly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42934:99"/>
beſeech thee by them to pardon theſe poore Soules all the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they haue committed againſt thee, through falſe, bitter, angry, or vaine wordes. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XI. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus, and repreſent vnto thee thy ſhamfull vncloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, when the cruell ſouldiers with furious haſt pulled off thy garments, &amp; thou meekly hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedſt them, it being thy deſire to ſuffer for vs; who hauing ſtriped thee naked bound thee to a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler with ſuch vnhumane cruelty that thy bloud guſhed forth at thy nayles, and they ſcourged thee ſo barbarouſly with whips wherin were Iron hooks, laying ſtripe vpon ſtripe, and wound vpon wound, that they rente &amp; tore thy ſacred body all ouer,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42934:100"/>
and lefte not ſo much as one whole peece of skin vpon thee; then they vnbound thee &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thy breaſt forward, bound thy handes ouer thy head, and ſcourged thee againe ſo cruelly on that ſide, that all thy ſacred fleſh being rent off, thy bones and bowells were diſcouered; then they vnlooſed thee from the Pillar, and in that lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner all-ouer wounded and imbrewed with thy bloud they put an old purple robe in ſcorne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee: O deereſt Lord I render thee infinite thankes for all theſe thy ſufferings and intollerable ſhame &amp; torments, and humbly beſeech thee by all the merits of them, and of thy ſacred wounds, and all the dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pps of thy moſt precious bloud that thou wilt haue mercy on theſe poore Soules, and pardon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42934:100"/>
all their ſinnes &amp; offences which they haue committed againſt thee. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Ieſus ſouerain king of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and ſhining crowne of the Saintes, and repreſent vnto thee how thoſe cruel miſcreats after they had ſo inhumanly ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thee, ſet vpon thy ſacred head a Crowne of ſharpe and pricking thornes, which they ſtrooke with cruell blowes into thy head, and kneeling downe before thee in ſcorne, ſaluted thee ſaying, All haile king of the Iewes; after which they pulled of the Crowne of thornes and ſet it on againe with intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tormentes to thee, ſpitting on thy diuine face which was all ouer imbrued with bloud,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42934:101"/>
ſwelled, disfigured, and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, giuing thee cruell buffets, ſcorning and deriding thee; O deereſt Lord Ieſus, O moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father and Sauiour, we repreſente vnto thee, all theſe paines, and do giue thee infinite thankes for all theſe thy ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and thoſe moſt cruell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thou enduredſt in thy ſacred head, moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching thee by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mercifully to pardon theſe poore ſoules all they haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by their head, either in hearing, ſeeing, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, eating, drinking, or vaine attyring of their heads, or by euill vſing the three powers of their ſoule; forgiue it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſweet Lord throgh thy infinit mercy. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XIII. PRAYER</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Ieſus eternall king of glory
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42934:101"/>
and repreſent vnto thee the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable ſhame, and torment thou dideſt endure when Pilate led thee out to the people, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the crowne of thornes and purple garment, &amp; ſaid, Behold the man, and the curſed multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſeeing thee ſo miſerably disfigured, wounded, rent, and torne, had no compaſſion on thee, but moſt vnhumanly cryed out, take him a way, take him a way, crucify him, crucify him: O deereſt Lord we render infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite thankes to thee for theſe thy cruell torments, ſhame, and ignominies, and beſeech thee to preſent now thy ſelfe with them and all thy other merites vnto thy heauenly Father for theſe ſoules, for their eternall recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, and cloath them with thy merites, and ſo preſent them to him, as a fruite of thy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42934:102"/>
better paſſion. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XIV. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus, God of infinit Power and Maieſty, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto thee how Pilate go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Iudgment ſeat, cauſed thee to be broght againe before him (where thou ſtoodſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly with declined head &amp; eyes) &amp; ſaid to the Iewes, I haue cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected him, will you that I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe him, but they al cryed out crucify him, crucify him: then Pilate ſaid, Will you that I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe Barabbas, and crucify Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? they all cryed out, yes, let him be crucified for he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the ſhamfull death of the Croſſe; then Pilate waſhed his hands and ſaid, I am innocent of the bloud of this iuſt man; but they all cryed out, let his bloud
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42934:102"/>
be vpon vs and vpon our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. O deereſt Sauiour, O fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all goodneſſe, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercy and God of all conſolation, we call vpon thee with all our hartes, and with our ſoule, powers, forces, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, moſt humbly beſeeching thee, that thou wilt vouchſafe to let thy precious bloud, come as truly vpon theſe poore ſoules to the forgiuenes &amp; remiſsion of all their ſinnes, as it hath done vpon the Iewes to their eternall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation. Then Pilate gaue the ſentence of death againſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: O deereſt Sauiour through this ſentence of death, which thou receiuedſt with ſo great humility, we humbly beſeech thee mercifully to pardon theſe poore Soules, in whatſoeuer they haue offended by any euill or raſh iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42934:103"/>
either in thought, word, or deed. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XV. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Ieſus, moſt meeke bearer of our infirmities, and offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee that great charity wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou dideſt imbrace the heauy Croſſe that the cruell Iewes laid vpon thy wounded ſhoulders, the weight wherof cauſed thee to bow downe euen to the ground, being ſo faint that thou couldſt ſcarce go or draw thy breath, in which pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full plight thou wert dragged forward by the Iewes, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtrooke thee on thy ſacred head, and caſt ſtones &amp; filth at thee: O deereſt Lord through the heauy burthen of the Croſſe which thou ſo willingly cariedſt for our ſins, we beſech thee that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42934:103"/>
thou wilt deliuer theſe Soules from all their paines, &amp; through the great wound that the heauy Croſſe made in thy wounded ſhoulder, we beſeech thee to comfort them in the ſame holy wound; and by thy painfull footſteps, forgiue them their ſinnefull footſteps, &amp; lead them into thy eternall glory; and through the ſorrow of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Mother &amp; compaſſion thou haddeſt of her, pardon theſe poore Soules whatſoeuer they haue offended by omiſſion of their duty toward their parents either corporall or ſpirituall. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XVI. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus Chriſt who cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt the lillyes &amp; flowers with colours and beauty, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42934:104"/>
vnto thee thy painfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clothing, when before ſo many and ſo great a multitude of people they ſo furiouſly pulled of thy garments, which ſtuck ſo faſt to thy woundes that with the force of pulling them off they tore off alſo thy skin and fleſh, with moſt intollerable paine and torment to thee, who ſtoodeſt in that miſerable plight all ouer wounded rent &amp; torne naked &amp; trembling with cold and ſhame in the view of all the world, powring from all partes of thy ſacred body ſtreames of moſt precions bloud. O moſt ſweet Ieſus, neuer did Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome goe to the chamber of his ſpouſe with ſo great a loue as thou wenteſt towardes the Croſſe: O deereſt Sauiour ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer did Prince go to receiue his Crowne more willingly then
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42934:104"/>
thou we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſt to the croſſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe impious vile miſcrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts moſt furiouſly caſt thee, &amp; thou moſt willing didſt ſtretch forth thy holy body vpon it, ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them moſt inhumanly to ſtretch forth, and to nayle thy right Hand thereunto, with a rough and boyſtorous nayle. O ſoueraigne Lord and ſweet Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer we re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der infinite tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to thy goodneſſe, for all theſe thy cruell paines and torments, and beſeech thee by them all to forgiue theſe poore Soules, all they haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded throgh pride of cloaths, or any other offence or ſinne. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XVII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Ieſus, deere Father of our ſoules, and preſent to thee that furious cruelty wherwith thoſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42934:105"/>
barbarous wretches drew thy other Hand with a cord vnto the hole they had made in the Croſſe, in ſuch ſort that thy bones were diſioynted, thy woundes rent wider, and all thy veines and ſinewes broken, and then they nayled that hand vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Croſſe as they had done the other. O deereſt Lord we render thee infinite thankes for that intollerable torment thou didſt endure in that cruell nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thy Handes vnto the croſſe, and beſeech thee by it &amp; by the ſacred woundes of them that thou wilt mercifully par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don theſe poore Soules all the ſinnes and offences, which by their handes they haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt thee. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XVIII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus, mercifull Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42934:105"/>
betweene thy heauenly Father &amp; vs ſinners, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to thee that cruelty wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the curſed Iewes ſtretched forth thy ſacred leggs ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently with a cord, that all thy veines &amp; ſinewes were broken, and nayled thy holy feet vnto the croſſe with great and boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous nayles, throgh thy great patience ſuffering them to do to thee whatſoeuer they would, as if thou hadſt ſaid, I lye heere to the end I may accompliſh my Fathers will, and redeeme man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. O what great and exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue paine cauſed euery ſtroke of the hammer vnto thy hart, and alſo to the tender hart of thy bleſſed Mother! O deereſt Sauiour, we render thee infinite thankes for that moſt intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable torment which thou didſt endure in that dolourous nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42934:106"/>
of thy ſacred feet, and that immenſe loue &amp; charity wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou dideſt ſuffer it, moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſeeching thee therby to pardon theſe ſoules all they haue committed againſt thee by ſitting, or lying, ſleeping, or waking, knowing or not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or in what ſort ſoeuer, through thy painfull lying on the croſſe and extreme torments ſhame and ignominy. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XIX. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>O Moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus we humbly ſalute thee, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent vnto thee that pittifull rearing vp of the croſſe, wherby thy cruell enemies did miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſhake thy ſacred body, vſing many clamours, opprobries and iniurious deſpites againſt thee, letting the croſſe fall, after they had rayſed it, violently downe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42934:106"/>
into the hole they had made for it in the ground, through the force wherof all thy woundes were renewed and moſt cruelly rent and torne, out of which as from riuers, flowed forth thy precious bloud in great aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. O deereſt Sauiour with what infinite Charity diddeſt thou hang there to make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for all ſinnes paſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and to come, for which we render thee immortall thankes and humbly beſeech thee, to let one drop of that thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud which thou dideſt then ſheed, deſcend vpon theſe Soules for a full ſatisfaction of all the ſinnes they haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the whole courſe of their life. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XX. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus who knoweſt the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42934:107"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:42934:107"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:42934:108"/>
deſires of our harts before they be declared by wordes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to thee that great chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wherewith hanging on the croſſe thou dideſt pray for thy enemyes, ſaying, Father forgiue them, for they know not what they do, which mercifull prayer of thine was of ſuch force that it conuerted many of them that were guilty of thy bloud: O true comforter of all ſorrowfull hartes, we beſeech thee throgh the merit of that thy Prayer, that thou wilt vouchſafe now to pray to thy heauenly Father, for theſe poore ſoules that they may be as fully pardoned of all their ſinnes &amp; offences, as thoſe who were then receiued into grace through the merit of thy precious bloud. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="prayer">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:42934:108"/>
               <head>THE XXI. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô ſoueraigne Lord Ieſus ſweet Father of mercy, and repreſent to thee how hanginge betweene two thee us, the one wherof blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thee, the other beſought thee to be myndefull of him when thou cameſt in thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whom thou dideſt boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully pardon and receiue into thy mercy, in ſuch ſort as he was the firſt vnto whom thou dideſt promiſe paradiſe, throgh which bottomleſſe mercy we beſeech thee, as alſo throgh the merits of thy precious bloud which thou impartedſt to the Theefe, to let the ſame precious bloud deſcend now vpon theſe ſoules vnto a full forgiueneſſe of their ſinnes, and through thy infinite mercy bring them into
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42934:109"/>
thy euerlaſting glory. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord Ieſus, ſweet ſolace of the ſorrowfull, and offer vnto thee all that internall ſuffering thou haddeſt, ſeeing thy deere Mother ſtanding vnder the croſſe ouerwhelmed in a ſea of deadly anguiſhes through loue and compaſſion towardes thee, whom thou dideſt commend to thy beloued Diſciple <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> which greately renewed her griefe and bitter ſorrow for thy death; O deereſt Lord through this loue and care thou haddſt of thy ſweet Mother in thy tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we humbly commend vnto thy mercifull goodneſſe theſe ſoules, beſeechinge thee to deliuer them for all paines and torments, through thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42934:109"/>
and the merites of thy bleſſed Mother. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXIII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus ſoueraign ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of thy holy Church, and faithfull forgiuer of ſinnes, and offer vnto thee that ſorrowfull Prayer thou madeſt vnto thy heauenly Father when thou ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, my God my God why haſt thou forſaken me? he hauing left thy holy Humanity deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of all help and comfort in thoſe thy bitter anguſhes and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, for all which we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly thanke thee, &amp; beſeech thee by them, and the merits of thy ſacred Prayer, that thou wilt mercifully heare our humble prayers which we now preſent to thee for theſe poore ſoules &amp; deliuer them through thy infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42934:110"/>
mercy and merits from all their paines &amp; torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXIV. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô ſweet Ieſus fountaine of liuing waters, and repreſent vnto thee, how thou ſaidſt, I thirſt, which thirſt muſt needs be exceſſiue great, for that there was not left one drop of bloud in all thy whole body, but chiefly dideſt thou thirſt for our ſaluation, for which we humbly thanke thee, as alſo for the bitter gall &amp; ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell thou dideſt take, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſorrow thou hadſt, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that thy bitter death ſhold be loſt on ſo many ſoules, all which we humbly offer to thee ô moſt ſweet Sauiour, and beſeech thee that thou wilt let thy precious bloud deſcend on theſe poore Soules to refreſh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42934:110"/>
them, and to deliuer them from all their paines. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXV. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Ieſus, ineſtimable treaſure of the diuine riches, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto thee, how in the end of thy life thou calledſt to mind all the holy workes thou hadſt done all thy life, and in one ſumme offeredſt them all vp to thy celeſtiall Father, ſaying, It is conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mate; we moſt humbly beſeech thee to offer that ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable treaſure of thy merits which neuer diminiſheth, vnto thy heauenly Father for theſe Soules, and therewith pay all the debts of their ſinnes, and all other they are charged with. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXVI. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Ieſus, giuer of life to all
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42934:111"/>
creatures and ſoueraigne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder of life and death, and repreſent vnto thee thy lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table hanging vpon the Croſſe all deformed with bleedinge woundes, &amp; a deadly paleneſſe at the time of thy death, when caſting downe thy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly eyes which were dimmed with tears and began to breake with the anguiſhes of death, and decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thy head which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about with thornes, to ſhew thy Obedience to thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father and reconcile thy Church to him, thou rendredſt thy ſacred ſoule crying with a lowd voyce, Father into thy handes I commend my ſpirit. O crucifyed Lord as thou didſt commend thy ſweet ſpirit into thy Fathers handes, ſo we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend theſe poore Soules into thyne, beſeching thee to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42934:111"/>
them vnto thy heauenly Father, and offer thy precious bloud and bitter death vnto him for a full pardon and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all their ſinnes. O Lambe of God that taketh away the ſinnes of the world, we beſeech thee throgh thy ſeauen words which are full of mercy and myſtery, that thou wilt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pardon theſe poore ſoules whatſoeuer they haue offended in the ſeauen deadly ſinnes, or any branch of them. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXVII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus the vanquiſher of death, deſcending with the banner of thy croſſe into hell: O how were thoſe Priſoners which ſo many yeares with lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging deſires had expected thee comforted, when as they ſaw thee, and knew thee to be God
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42934:112"/>
and man, their Lord and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and that Adam ſaid, I ſee heere that hand that framed me: O deereſt Sauiour, we beſeech thee through the Ioy thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoules had when thou dideſt lead them out of that Infernall Priſon, and by that vnſpeakable gladneſſe thou hadſt when thou beheldeſt the firſt happy fruit of thy death and paſſion, through al thy merits, that thou wilt lead forth theſe poore ſoules out of all captiuity. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXVIII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine of loue and mercy, and repreſent to thee how <hi>Longinus</hi> furiouſly opened thy ſide with a ſpeare, which tranſpeirced euen thy Sacred hart, of out which flowed both water and bloud: O deereſt Lord, we humbly thanke thee
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42934:112"/>
for this moſt liberall effuſion of thy precious bloud, and humbly beſeech thee by it, to receiue theſe poore Soules into thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred woundes, and hart, and cleanſe them with thy precious bloud; and by the fiue woundes of thy handes, feet, and hart, &amp; all the other ſacred woundes of thy moſt precious body mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully to pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all their ſinnes. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXIX. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus the innocent ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed Lambe, &amp; repreſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee how thy wounded body was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe, &amp; laid in the lap of thy ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Mother, from which croſſe thou wouldſt not deſcend vntill thou haddſt accompliſhed the worlds redemption. O deereſt Lord, through that thy infinite
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42934:113"/>
mercy, and all other merites of thy bitter paſſion, we humbly beſeech thee to vnlooſe theſe poore ſoules fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the chaines wherewith they haue bound themſelues by their ſinnes: &amp; we humbly beſeech thee alſo, O Sacred Mother of God, through the ſorrow and tender compaſsion thou hadſt to ſee the wounded body of thy dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſonne lying dead in thy lap, that thou wilt offer his and thy merites for theſe poore Soules vnto the eternall Father to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a full pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; remiſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all their ſinnes. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXX. PRAYER</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus, and offer vnto thee thy holy buriall, how after all thy labours and miſeries, thou dideſt reſt in thy graue; We humbly beſeech thee, to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42934:113"/>
giue theſe ſoules reſt in the holy City of heauen, &amp; forgiue them who haue ſo often times with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne their ſoule from thee, by the diſtraction of temporall thinges, and not ſuffered thee, their peacefull king, to reſt in their hartes. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXXI. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus, the ioy of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and ſaluation of men, and repreſent to thee thy glorious reſurrection and ioyfull appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions to thy holy Mother, &amp; deere friends, through which we humbly beſeech thee, O con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querer of death, that thou wilt with thy diuine power ſhew thy ſelfe to theſe poore Soules, &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all their bitter paines. <hi>Miſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXXII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô ſoueraigne King of glory, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42934:114"/>
to thee thy Glorious Triumphant Aſcenſion, and Aſſumption of thoſe Soules which in Limbo ſo long time had expected their Rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, moſt humbly beſeeching thee ſweet Sauiour, that thou wilt be pleaſed, through thy infinite goodneſſe; to lead theſe Soules into thy eternall glory, where for euer they may behold thy diuine and heauenly face. O good Ieſus and deere Sauiour we beſeech thee by thy holy conuerſation, and painfull paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to pardon them all their ſinnes and bring them into thy eternall reſt, and fruition of thy glory. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="prayer">
               <head>THE XXXIII. PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE ſalute thee ô eternall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created Sonne of God, full of grace and mercy, the reward of all thoſe that hope in thee,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42934:114"/>
moſt humbly beſeeching thee, mercifully to forgiue vs all our omiſsions of intention in theſe prayers, &amp; let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be, throgh our coldnes, leſſe meritorious to theſe poore Soules, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them according to the worthineſe of the ſacred myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries mentioned therin, through that infinite loue wherewith they were accompliſhed, and the worthineſſe of the perſon that wrought them, by all which we humbly beſeech thee to deliuer theſe poore ſoules fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all paines and reioyce them with thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly preſence for all eternity. <hi>Miſerere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>O Moſt ſweet Lord Ieſus, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lord &amp; life of our ſoules, we humbly beſeech thee to encline thy eares to our prayers, &amp; deliuer theſe Soules
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42934:115"/>
(or this Soule) from all paines and admit them into thy eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall glory; Let thy preciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bloud, thy deep woundes, thy cruell torments, thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, innocent death, thy Nobl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Soule, and the prayers and me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rits of thy ſacred Mother, and all the holy Angels and Saintes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be vnto them a full ſatisfaction for all their ſinnes, negligences, and omiſsions; and ſuffer no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Soules, whom thou haſt redeemed with thy preciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bloud, any longer to be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thee. O Redeemer o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the world we hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly offer theſe prayers for them, to thy ttanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peirced Hart, beſeeching thee to grant them the fruition of thy eternall Glory. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42934:115"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42934:116"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42934:116" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
